<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The philosopher of the court, written by Philbert of Vienne in Champaigne, and Englished by George North, gentlema[n].</title>
            <title>Philosophe de court. English</title>
            <author>Philibert, de Vienne, 16th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114638</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849863</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 388:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The philosopher of the court, written by Philbert of Vienne in Champaigne, and Englished by George North, gentlema[n].</title>
                  <title>Philosophe de court. English</title>
                  <author>Philibert, de Vienne, 16th cent.</author>
                  <author>North, George, gentleman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 114, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Binnema[n], for Lucas Harison and George Byshop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Le philosophe de court.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:1"/>
            <head>To the right <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Master Chriſtopher</hi> Hatton Eſquier, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Queenes Maieſties <hi>Garde, and Gentleman of bir</hi> highneſſe priuie Chamber.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT noble Stoicke Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca (right vvorſhipfull) to vvhome all the ancients paſt yelded place &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie for Morall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, ſhut vp in this ſhorte ſentence reaſons of great ſubſtance, ſaying: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is euer fleting, for ſhe neuer giueth ioy vvithout heauineſſe, ſvveete vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bitterneſſe, reſt vvithout trauell, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noume vvithout enuie, and generally, no felicitie vvithout ſome ſequele of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie. This I preſently find verefied in myſelf, vvhile motioned by glad minde and duetifull good vvill to ſhroude this little labor vnder the protection of your
<pb facs="tcp:15035:2"/>
vvorſhips fauoure, I feele double feare to front my proceeding: youre noble vvorthy neſſe and my baſhfull rudeneſſe, vvhich both are repugnant to my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire: yet matching the firſte vvyth the goodneſſe of youre nature (compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to encounter force vvith force) and mating the laſt vvith the profoundneſſe of my Author, I preſume to preſent the ſame vnto you, entituled the <hi>Philoſopber of the Court,</hi> and dedicated to his Ladie a louer of vertue. The name and dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeemeth of ſome credite, but the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and concluſion I can not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently commende. Great volumes haue large fieldes to marche in, and ſo muche the more laborſome to peruſe: but if it pleaſe youre vvorſhip to tread ouer this little Treatiſe, I dare aduouch, you ſhall finde in it, both floures and fruite (not to ſupply the ſcarcetie, but to encreaſe the plentie and pleaſaunte purpoſes) of Courtly Philoſophie. VVherein as my ignorance ſhall eclipſe or ſhadovve the vvorthyneſſe of the vvorke: Spread (I
<pb facs="tcp:15035:2"/>
humbly praye) the gladſome beames of your fauourable and vvell liking cheere vpon it: ſo ſhall you render to the reader my Author much betterd, make him of other gentlemen Courtiers more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, my pen to further trauell encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and my ſelfe in this enterpriſe moſt glad and pleaſed. Heere ſome curious man may controll me for preſuming to tranſlate, profeſsing (as neceſſitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth) a harder condition, and ſaye: a vvriter of a Souldier? vvhy? the pen and pyke doe differ, Mars and Minerua are contrarie, Bellona is nothing pleaſed vvith bokes: yet Poets haue oft painted Pallas that Academicall Goddes to be armed vvith ſpeare and ſhield. Time, and the intent vvell employed, is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued. And Cicero pleading <hi>pro Planco</hi> ſaythe: <hi>Otij non minus quàm negotij ratio extare debet.</hi> Therefore to encounter any ſuche callendge, I enforce my beſt endeuer vvith the aſſured ſupply of your noble fauour, and remaine for euer (in either fortune) <hi>propoſſe,</hi> your vvorſhips humble Souldier.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George North.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:3"/>
            <head>10. Daniell.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE buzzing Bee and Spyder eke, forth of one bud done finde</l>
               <l>Both healthſome iuyce and venome vile, yet each contents his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And mongst all things men chooſe the beſt, and done them daily vſe,</l>
               <l>But good men vſen good things well, bad men done them abuſe.</l>
               <l>We knowe that fire and water bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e can forbeare,</l>
               <l>And yet oft times we ſee them both, how e they abuſed are.</l>
               <l>By firie flames and flowing floudes, we ſee much miſchiefe fall.</l>
               <l>As countries drownde, and cities burnd, my ſelfe haue knowne them all:</l>
               <l>And yet the Bee, and best men eke, which vſe good things aright,</l>
               <l>Deſeruen praiſe by iudgement mine, in ſpite of ſpitefull ſpite.</l>
               <l>And nowe <hi>George North</hi> compare may well, with good men and with Be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>For he the worſe doth hate, and best doth praiſe, as we may ſee</l>
               <l>By booke of his, which here we may, peruſe and eke beholde:</l>
               <l>A frenchman ſtraunge, by North his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yle an engliſh tale hath told,</l>
               <l>To ſhew what Philoſophus is, if it be taken right,</l>
               <l>And howe by corrupt worldlymen, it is abuſed quite.</l>
               <l>But N. I. knewe his meaning is, that all things would be better,</l>
               <l>If taken right, Philoſophus, were from the greekiſh letter:</l>
               <l>And that is, as I vnderſtand, diuine wiſdome to loue,</l>
               <l>And leaue ſuch wiſdome as the world doth daily to vs moue.</l>
               <l>Wherefore O North my friendly friend, I muſt needes yelde thee praiſe,</l>
               <l>For that in vertue ſuch I ſee thee ſeeke to ſpende thy dayes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>William Hitchockes Gent.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE pricking ſpurre doth keepe the trampling ſteed in awa,</l>
               <l>The haling horſe is driuen, with laſhing whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to drawe,</l>
               <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing Aſſe is forst, by bruſing bat to toyle,</l>
               <l>The pearcing goade doth make the painefull Oxe to moyle:</l>
               <l>The goade, the whip, the bat, and ſpur, which only driue</l>
               <l>To tende the painefull path where vertue wonts to liue,</l>
               <l>Is praiſe: why then giue praiſe (which is the good and ſpur,</l>
               <l>The whip and bat whereby each doth in vertue ſtur)</l>
               <l>To him that did tranſlate: thy ſelfe ſhalt thereby gaine</l>
               <l>To force him for thy ſake, to take much greater paine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:3"/>
            <head>The Argument of the Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat ſtrife hath grovvne vvith elders ſage in ſearch of ſoueraine good,</l>
               <l>The vviſer ſort deemd Nature it, but nought they vnderſtoode:</l>
               <l>Our Soueraine good framd Nature baſe, to him vve thanks muſt yeld,</l>
               <l>VVe vvrought ſelfe thrall, yet he in loue made gracious Chriſte our shielde.</l>
               <l>But ſith they erred, and ſeeming graue miſtoke good on this ſort,</l>
               <l>Giue yong men ſeaue for learnings ſake to ſpeake their minds in ſport.</l>
               <l>I take our ſoueraine good to be, to liue in Court aright,</l>
               <l>VVith prudent care to ſeeke our gaints, of artes to haue ſome ſight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>In Iuſtice to do no man vvrong, to giue great thankes to vvin,</l>
               <l>For Fame to crouch, or fight for right, shift poore, shift friend, shift kin,</l>
               <l>To temper talke and deeds vvith ſuch as further may our fetch,</l>
               <l>VVith haughtie lokes to shun the lavvs, and graſp vvithin our reach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Philoſophers vvould thinke it nevve, but reaſon vvils them ſtay,</l>
               <l>For they haue ſpoke: indifferent doome muſt beare the bell avvay.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:4"/>
            <head>The Prologue, or Authors Epiſtle, to his Ladie, a louer of vertue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall now ſee moſte noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, whither the doubtfull opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that you haue long tyme had of mee: which I haue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beene hythertoo able by reaſons or excuſe to remooue, may by the troth it ſelfe make you of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudgement. For it is not once, twice, or thrice that you haue reproued mee, to bee a promiſer, a deceyuer, and ſuch a one as ye perceyued (as you tolde mee your ſelfe) to bee worthy of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no credit at all: Notwithſtanding that in all my promiſes, or any other wayes withoute promiſe, wherein my humble ſeruice might be moſt agreable and beſt liked of you, I haue not fayled, either in deſire, or execution. But this is none other than the naturall diſpoſition of you Gentlewomen, ſtill to pick ſuche quarels: when (according to your good cuſtome) you deſyre any thing, bee it neuer ſo wayghtie, weake, or daungerouſe: your longing for the ſame is ſo greate, that without conſideration, of the opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitye, the eaſineſſe, or the poſſibilitie, you
<pb facs="tcp:15035:5"/>
thinke on nothing elſe, but on the neceſsitie to haue it done. And if the ende ſucceede not as you wiſhe, you lay the faulte vpon your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes, whome afterwardes you call lyars and promiſers. Yet whatſoeuer I ſay, though it bee reported to bee a common faulte in women, I will not mainteyne the ſame to bee in you: For knowing your noble minde aboue others, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſo loftie a ſeate, as ſeeing and vewing a farre off the ſmall faultes, errours, and abuſes, wherin their Ignorance may bee wrapped: your wiſedome I nothing doubt, is able well ynough to auoyde it: beeing exempted from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſorte, and contrarie too ſuche waywarde conditions. I will then perſwade my felfe, that ſuche reproche (if it may ſo bee called) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from a good minde, and of good will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſure that you knowe mee otherwiſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you. And therefore by the waye haue ſayd it, rather to aduertiſe me, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I ſhould ſeeme ſuche to you, or you account ſo of mee, but rather bycauſe I ſhould become ſuch a one, euen as it often fareth with thoſe, that being in feare, commonly complayne before they feele any greefe. Yet can I not content my ſelfe with this perſwaſion, ſeeing that my affection ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes not to bee ſo entier lie knowen vnto you, while ye make ſo little accompt of it. Therfore
<pb facs="tcp:15035:5"/>
to gyue you better teſtimonie of that you are ſo doubtfull to beleeue, and to the end that by this argument, you maye hope for better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hereafter, of that whiche (it may be) yee ſuſpect. For (I deſire rather to ſatisfie you, than my ſelfe, thoughe I haue iuſter cauſe too ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect you, than you mee) after my departure from <hi>Paris,</hi> expelling and chaſing from mee ſundrie fantaſies, by the abſent remembrance of your ſo good a will, whiche ordinarie preſence woulde not ſuffer: I enterpriſed this trauell, to write this little treatiſe vnto you, packing vp in this ſo ſmall a volume, the delightfull inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> and manner how to lyue: in the which we paſſed this melancholike tyme of winter, where, and in what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie you knowe: mingling our other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon paſtimes, with this Noble diſcourſe. I am not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tneſſe of your deſire, to vnderſtand the troth in all things: for when as ſomtimes beeing with you, betweene our ſelues, I would aſſaye to be come a good Orator: you by importunate meane, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained me to become a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher.<note place="margin">Yong yeares meeteſt for the ſtudie of Philoſophie.</note> And I pray you who are meeter to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie:</hi> that is to ſearche the knowledge of God, &amp; of man, to know who we are, where we are, wherefore wee are, and howe wee ſhoulde gouerne and guyde oure lyues one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:15035:6"/>
than oure yonger people? VVho by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of greene yeares and ſmall experience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not yet their iudgementes certaine or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but wild and raſh, and till the ſcum &amp; filth of youthfull heate bee boyled oute of them, are but little profitable to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe. O what a laudable cuſtome were it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, if the adminiſtration of common wealth, were not committed and put on ſuche as are yong, rude, and of no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and that ſuch in no wiſe ſhoulde gouerne or giue counſell, till they were throughly tried and approued. Then the people ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo muche daunger, and they in applying ſome payne to diſcretion, ſhould in the ende, be moſt profitable to themſelues: For it would be a great contentment to their life (after experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had) and ſpecially, their olde age would not be ſo melancholy, angrie, impacient, and waywarde, in digeſting all things euill. For<note place="margin">Experience n akes age <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſie.</note> what made <hi>Cato</hi> the elder, as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke <hi>de Senectute,</hi> ſayth, to beare his yeares ſo paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, too bee ſo pleaſant. and well diſpoſed an olde man, and (which is more marueylous) to bee ioyfull and merie in yong and youthfull companie, but the great knowledge, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience he had in all things? I feele my ſelfe to ſtray from my firſt intent, and by little and little
<pb facs="tcp:15035:6"/>
to fall from my purpoſe: It is then requiſite for youth, to vſe and acquaint themſelues to a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie and contemplate life, not as Hermites in the wilderneſſe, or lyke Monkes in the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: but ſuche a ſure and diligent meane, as they may bee capable, to informe, and inſtruct themſelues in time to all good things: So that when the ſpirite is thus framed and taught, and the furious flame of youth put out: they may the ſooner and better exerciſe the life actiue, and then take vpon them, to trauell for the common wealth of their Countrey. If my head and bearde were ſomewhat gray in ſiluer ſhewe anſwerable to this cauſe, I woulde make an inuectiue, and declame agaynſt this fooliſhe, brutiſh, and vnbridled youth, which delightes not but in vnprofitable matters, and voyde of reaſon, neuer regarding nor following other guyde than Careleſneſſe, accounting it ſhame, and reproch to be ſeene or thought to doe any thing for good purpoſe. And (if you will noble Ladie, pardon me priuately to reproue you) I cannot wonder ynough to ſee, that among you worthie Damſels, being (as you are) the iudges,<note place="margin">Ladies are the patrons and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the priuiledges of youth.</note> patrones and preſeruers of the priuiledges of youth: howe you can commonly approue and allow thoſe vnprofitable actions, in doltes and beaſts of no courage, ſomtime proceeding of an
<pb facs="tcp:15035:7"/>
euill nature: and yet they haue ſuch place with you, that being in your Court men lawded and glorious flatterers, you reioyce with them, and equally fauour them, as pleaſant and worthie ſeruaunts. It woulde very well become (as it ſeemeth vnto me) yong men, to employ this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and pleaſant time of youthfull yeares, in the knowledge of vertue, and in other commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable exerciſes of the bodie, as wreſtling, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſhewed both valure &amp; vertue: To the end that being ſo experimented, feeling their owne ſtrength, and comming too mans ſtate, they neede not any longer to learne how they ought to liue. For ſo ſoone as a man commes either to ſerue the common wealth, or to haue care of his houſholde: he ſhould no more be a ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, but rather an inſtructer. VVho if he will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter breake his braynes about <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting his charge, and regarding not his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>Plato</hi> willes, he ſhoulde bee turned to play with nuttes among boyes, and whipped wyth roddes among children. And for this purpoſe, I deſire you noble Damſell, to reade one peece in <hi>Plato</hi> of <hi>Gorgias,</hi> beginning with this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (for there he teacheth, why, howe, where, and when <hi>Philoſophie</hi> is to be vſed,) <hi>Philoſophie</hi> ſayth he, is an excellent thing and very ſeemely, ſo that it be vſed moderately, ſoberly, and in due
<pb facs="tcp:15035:7"/>
time of yeares: wherein if any plunge themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues too deepe, it deſtroyeth them vtterly. It may ſeeme by this, that <hi>Plato</hi> reproues indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, the perfit knowledge of <hi>Philoſophie:</hi> yet truly he neither deſpiſeth nor diſprayſeth it, but ſo far as it is vnprofitable and hindreth vs from our other needfull affayres. For ſince that all ſciences were inuented for the helpe of man, and as much for the conſeruation of the Soule, the bodie and goodes, as conſequently to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne a ſocietie, companie, and felowſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: To what purpoſe then, doe anye breake their braynes in their ſtudies, if it be not for profite to themſelues, or benefite to ſome others? Conſidering therefore that you haue your witte at libertie, rouing at will, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your pleaſant ſteppes at randon, where beſt liketh your youthful yeres to carrie you (though it ſomewhat yeldeth to naturall affection) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low I pray you your firſt intent, and there ſhall want no good will in me, ſeeing I prepare my ſelf to matters of greater importance than this, and other matters alſo, but that your deſire ſhall be ſatiſfied. Yet I knowe that this worde <hi>Philoſophie</hi> doeth ſounde ſo hatefull in the eares of manye, thoughe ſome falſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll opinion they haue of <hi>Philoſophie</hi> too them vnknowne: that they will thinke it
<pb facs="tcp:15035:8"/>
ſtraunge and abſurde to peruert or mar (for ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey terme it) ſo excellent a perfection of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, as is in you, with ſo melancholike opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns. Therefore this I will ſay: ſeeing they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her know nor hate Philoſophie, but onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he name, let vs leaue the worde, and ſpeake no more of it: but let vs ſay, that you do learne howe to lyue in the worlde: which all perſons do couet too knowe, and yet too liue in the worlde is no other thing than the ſame which we call or tearme Philoſophie, as we wil proue hereafter, wherein, it would greeue mee, (fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing my purpoſe) if you and I, ſhoulde ſo much vſe our iudgements, and with ſuch hote affection, that wee forget to knowe our ſelues, and ſo make vs mockeries and laughingſtockes to the worlde. I thinke it not good to haue my houſe of a tunne as <hi>Diogenes</hi> had: nor to ſcratch out my eyes as <hi>Democritus</hi> did: or die for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as hee that had his <hi>Maliſſa,</hi> the better too know and vnderſtand Philoſophie. But I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and prayſe him, who making good ohere, louing good wine, and ſeeking good felowſhip, can by the waye contemplate and marke the maner and liuing of euery one: and conſider of thoſe that do both good and euill, the vantage of either. In thus vſing the mother of all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,<note place="margin">Philoſophie the mother of Sciences.</note> ſhe will neuer make any heauie nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie
<pb facs="tcp:15035:8"/>
or as (ſome report) by inordinate ſtudy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie: but ſhe may drawe them from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and ſundry follies, that ſmell more brutiſhe than manlie. And if any will ſay that withoute this, euery man may liue: I dare affirme, that he is ſo farre from reaſon, as his opinion deſerues no anſwere. As for the pleaſure, deſire, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment that comes of it, thus muche may be ſayde: that if in the morning, when you attire your ſelfe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g your maidens, the cleere chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall, and good looking glaſſe, delightes you, in ſhewing the perfit Image of your outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion: how much more ſhoulde you reioyce to beholde and ſee your ſelfe in this Science, to knowe what is your life, what it ought too bee, what you are, and what is the ſubſtance of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie thing? Heereby you ſhall learne, howe the wyfe ought too gouerne and behaue hir ſelfe, with hir husbande: it ſheweth howe you ſhall well inſtruct and guyde your houſeholde: your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle priuate common wealth ſhall be ſo neate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd poliſhed, as nothing better: you ſhall know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe to vſe your ſelfe towarde ſtraungers: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou may bee aſſured by this, without reproofe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do any thing freelie, for infamie and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſhall no way torment you. VVhat woulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou wiſhe or deſire more? On the contrarie, withoute this knowledge, you remaine in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence
<pb facs="tcp:15035:9"/>
and doubt, like too a traueler beeing in the open fielde and preſſed on his iourney, not knowing his way: you haue no other guide, than that blinde beaſt of common and popular iudgement, who (as ignorant and vnexpert in all things) ſayeth and doth one while one thing and an other while an other. For what is more inconſtant than Ignorance? Thus being bound to this fooliſhe, variable, and common opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hauing no other reaſon or councell, but to followe others: you ſhall ſoone vnderſtand in what miſeries and care you liue. Knowing therfore your ſo good affection, and to the end to deliuer you out of his priſon and miſerable darkeneſſe of Ignorance, I haue written to you this little treatiſe, altogither rude and impoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderer through the countrie: In the which you ſhall breefely ſee the ſumme of that I euer thought in Philoſophy: wherin the auncient &amp; Sages paſt repoſed their ſoueraine bountie: Then howe it is in theſe dayes diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and masked, grounded onely on mans opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and not on Nature: And laſt, you ſhall amply finde (yet not ſo much as I gladly would) what I thinke of this newe <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> which is the order and manner of liuing in theſe dayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In writing whereof I haue played <hi>Democrates,</hi> &amp; applyed the whole too a pleaſant concluſion.
<pb facs="tcp:15035:9"/>
Therefore when you vnderſtande the one and the other, you will vſe it (I know) ſo diſcretely, that it ſhall not let you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your neceſſarie cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of more importance. And if in the diſcourſe of the booke, I ſpeak more vnciuilly and boldly than is meete or conuenient to your excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: It may pleaſe you payſe thoſe woordes and ſentences, in the balance apte and conuenient to the matter heere treated, whiche hath ofte &amp; in many places made me forget the ſweete and gentle ſtyle that ye might deſire. To conclude, I humbly requeſt you to receyue this my little labour, as the frute of your owne poſſeſsion &amp; inheritance: wherby I ſhall ſeeme to haue gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned great profit, if it pleaſe you to preſerue it &amp; cloſe it in the coffer of your gracious fauour: wherewith I haue nothing too wiſhe or deſire, but the immortalitie of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:10"/>
            <head>The Philoſophie of <hi>the Court.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He auncient <hi>Philoſophers</hi> paſt whoſe morall iudgementes were allowed for doctrine in their time, did all affirme that nature hath giuen vs nothing euil: and if in our life we would follow, or do no more than we are naturally enclined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and that which ſhe preſcribeth, we ſhould neuer doe any thing but well. But if wée growe déeper into conſideration of the cauſe, and come nearer the quicke, whiche they could not ſo well attaine to, as we may (who haue our eyes open and cléered by him from whence procéedeth this nature, of which they ſpeake ſo much, and which tooke that name through ignorance of him: For who is it elſe that we ſhould cal Nature, if we beléeue God to be the creator of all things?) It will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeare, that thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entence is truer than they thinke for. They ſay, the inſtinct of nature, ſufficeth only to liue will: and we likewiſe affirme the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: yet they knowe not that the well liuing whereof we ſpeake, is perfiter than their <hi>Philoſophicall</hi> liuing, which in reſpect of ours is moſt vnlike well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15035:11"/>
liuing. Notwithſtanding wée affirme as they, and agrée with them, that nature hath giuen vs ſufficient ayde and helpe too lyue well. But to the ende wée enter not intoo errour, or ſéeme to depraue God of due glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which I ſpeake for his honour: I will not ſay that this nature which I now ſpeake of, and the philoſophicall reaſon is all one. For the nature whereof I now write, is the firſt nature, not corrupt or filthie, or blinde, but ſuch as knew no ſinne, nor taſted of any other thing, than the bleſſing of God. This I am ſure hath no parte in euill: I call that euill according to the ballance and meaſure wherewyth wée trie good and euill at theſe dayes, whiche is muche iuſter and harder than the tryall of <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> But ſince it bath bene corrupted and touched by oure enimye, it ſtyll abydeth lame and vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: And (that is worſe) it cannot acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what it was at the firſt, nor conceyue from whence it tooke begynning, except it bel ightned by a ſpirituall clearneſſe, which theſe <hi>Philoſophers</hi> had not. Euen ſo thys ſeconde Nature ſoyled in fylthe as ſhée is, is the ſame that the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſo muche ſpeake of and meane (for they knewe no better) but this is nothing to ſatiſfie Gods
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15035:11"/>
iuſtice, or the good lyfe requyred of vs by hym: but is rather a hurte and hinderance too the ſame. Yet otherwyſe to make a man iuſt, wyſe, graue, and vertuous, among men, which is the accompliſhing of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> nature can doe all. For the ſpirit of man can perceyue no imperfite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this nature béeing ſo ſpoyled, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and weake: yet hauing this vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and iudgement (whiche is abyding in this ſeconde Nature) that God hathe not made anye thing euyll: and beléeuing that this ſeconde Nature is the firſt, not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but made of God as in déede it is, and that there is no other: hée wéenes all to bée well, and ſuppoſes all operations procéeding from this to bée perfite good, and eſtemes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is done by the ſame for vertue. This is (as I coniecture) all the ſcience and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> This is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our graue and ſage fellowes of the worlde, that haue ſo arrogantly vaunted of this great dame vertue. Theſe are the cauſes that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawes ciuil, which is part of their <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie,</hi> do ſuffer ſome things repugnant to gods ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as kéeping of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cubines, to repell by forée, (which they ſay is natural) any preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with brech of faith, &amp; ſuch like
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15035:12"/>
We will therefore ſpeake as they, and with them, but with an other intent: not intrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting ſo much of their true vertue, as of any other diſguiſed and maſking vertue, which men doe followe and honour in ſteade of the right: to the end the world may know theyr double follie and ignorance: for hauing found this laſt and newe vertue, they haue not that they ſuppoſe: and thoughe they had it, yet ſhould they haue nothing.</p>
            <p>Nature therefore (to ſpeake as a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher)<note place="margin">Nature is the mother of all good things.</note> is the mother of all good things, and the ſame which prouokes vs to vertue. Then it muſt néedes followe, that we are naturally borne to doe good, and that ſhée ſoweth in our myndes, certaine ſmall ſparckles of good will: which if we quench by wicked cuſtome of doing euill, we ought not to imputo the ſame to nature, for none can iuſtly ſay that naturally any is euill. Theſe ſmall ſparkes are ſtirring ſharp prickes, that ſtill do moue and incourage vs, to doe thoſe things which are good of themſelues. So that after the firſt prouoking motion whiche commeth of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the alone and onely goodneſſe of thoſe cauſes, is the finall ende which draweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s therevnto. This is the ſame that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> treates of in the firſt of his <hi>Ethikes,</hi> who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15035:12"/>
perſwades what vertue is, and howe it may be knowne, ſaying: <hi>Si quispiam rerum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendarum est finis, quem nos propter ſeipſam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petimus, constat hunc talem finem ſummum bonum, ipſumque, optimum eſse. <hi>If there bee in our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings any ende, the which we deſire for it ſelfe: it confirmes that this ende is the ſoueraine good, and that in the ſame conſiſteth vertue.</hi>
               </hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wée muſte beléeue that if any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or cauſe make vs to doe anye act, than ſuche as beſéemeth honeſtie, and notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſame ſéeme lawfull &amp; laudable, yet is it not good. Vertue will bée loued on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for hir owne ſake, which is a point wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many (but of meane vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding) though of ſufficient iudgement, are oft deceyued: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſée a man of good courage, enforce him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with great paine to do any thing that ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes good in itſelfe: as to helpe his neighbor, or well to ſerue his maſter: or to defende his ſubiects: ſo ſoone as they knowe it done, they ſtraight eſtéeme him an honeſt man: nothing conſidering why he did it: either for reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a good man, or to be better recompenced than be deſerued, whereby he might defraude another wel deſeruer, or for feare of reproch if he ſhould not do it: by which it may appéere vnto vs, that thoſe works which to vs ſéeme
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15035:13"/>
beſt are nothing worth, we muſt not iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny work according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhew, but according to the cauſe and intent of the doer. For (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> ſaith) vertue and vice conſiſt in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and not in the worke. Therefore we muſt be more carefull to beware that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhew of good deceiue vs no more, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the apparance of euill. For a maſked euill, is a double miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: and no euil is ſo dangerous, as prefered &amp; well ſeeming goodneſſe which is called hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. Wherein <hi>Cicero</hi> tooke ſome paine in the firſt booke of his Offices, at the end of the Chapter, beginning: <hi>Sed ea animi elatio, &amp;c.</hi> ſpeaking of magnani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itie, where he ſayth, that it is raſhly &amp; tauntingly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we ſhoulde take in hande &amp; interpriſe any hard, dangerous and worthie attempt, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of glorie: for that there are few found (as he affirmeth) who after they haue done any thing valiantly or worthily, are not glad to be prayſed, eſtéeming this pomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of rurall brute, a triumphant reward of their well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But I beleue <hi>Cicero</hi> then thought of him ſelfe: for ſuppoſing that ſome knew him very couetous of honour, &amp; yet would ſéeme neble minded &amp; vertuous, he would not altegither ſeparat this deſire of glory fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity.</p>
            <p>The hope of prai ſe ſhould incourage the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15035:13"/>
to do well, and to exerciſe the ſame, by which exerciſe they may accuſtom the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to vertue, that by little &amp; little they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good men: and when they are become ſuch, the loue of vertue only will make them do well, and no cauſe elſe. We deſire and loue many other things, not for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of others, as money to be mery with, &amp; health to be at our eaſe: ſo that hauing both mony &amp; helth, and wanting our eaſe, we ſhuld not be ſatiſfied. But vertue is of greater value, &amp; of more price with vs: for ſhe alone pleaſeth vs: and we deſire to do well, only for that it is good to do wel, &amp; to none other ende. Nature the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> makes vs loue ſuch things as ar good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; this loue by hir, is ſo firmly fixed in vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> howſoeuer nature is corrupted &amp; altred, yet is ſhe ſtil inclined &amp; drawn to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which ſéemes to hir beſt: &amp; this ſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce daily foloweth the qualitie and condition of nature. For as long as ſhe is ſound and not corrupted, ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g good things in their perfection ſeeme alſo good, and follow hir. On the contrary part, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature is corrupted, reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſlepe, luſt &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it gouern, black ſemeth white, &amp; euil good: the wickedſt works ſeme to hir good, ſhe cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth holde on them, ſhe followeth them and doeth as much miſchiefe as may be, and ſo makes a vertue of that which in déed is vice.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15035:14"/>
This is the ſame that the Poet ment, ſaying: <hi>Decipimur ſpecie recti, <hi>The apparance of good deceyueth vs,</hi>
               </hi> not for that the good chaungeth, or ſheweth it ſelf at any time otherwiſe than it is: but our naturall iudgement being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and blind, ſo miſtakes it. Since therfore the fragilitie and weakneſſe of our nature is ſo great, that vnwares to vs, ſléepingly, and as in a dreame, ſhe chaungeth hirſelfe: if we haue not diligent regarde (for this worlde is no other than full of allurements to vice) ſhe being once altered, the ſemblance and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on likewiſe altereth, &amp; new affections enter, to ſerue this newe appetite, as it fareth with ſome king entring into his newe kingdome, where proweſſe is not vſed, &amp; the wandring mind caried indifferently either one way or other: and therefore it is commonly ſayd that vertue is the centre or midſt of vice: for none can ſo little decline to any ſide, but falleth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one vice or other. We ought then to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull to nouriſh and maintaine this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in hir ſimplicitie, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſhe is, before ſhe be more decayed, and to prop hir vp on euery ſide, lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhe reele bither or thither. I call it reeling or ſtaggring, when by our negligence and ignorance, we ſuffer our ſelues to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with euery fond opinion, conceyt or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15035:14"/>
maner of life that takes vs in the heade, and to giue hir armor and weapons, as wel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend as to vanquiſh hir enimies that ſeeke to make hir yéeld, which we may eaſily do by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true knowledge of good from euil, and not by fraud &amp; frequentation of the world. Or rather (if it be tollerable in me to tread a little out of the Philoſophers tract, &amp; ſpeak the truth) we ought to enforce our ſelues, to deface &amp; extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the vice of the ſecond nature by faith, &amp; to reenter into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pureneſſe &amp; cleanneſſe of the firſt: which the Philoſophers (as I haue ſayd afore) knew not, as we do, and better may, if we open the gate to him that ſayth vnto vs: Behold I am at your doore and knock there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, to them that open I will enter, and eate with them and they with me.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that doth ſooner chaunge the affection and condition of mans life: or (to ſpeake more plainly) our nature, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. This ſimilitude &amp; reſemblance, that all men take one of another by the capable conceyt of reaſon, is of ſo great force that like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſort be, the reſt wil ſeke to be like vnto them. And though ſome delight to be contrary in maner of liuing, to the place &amp; countrey they are in, the reaſon is, they haue ſeene others do the ſame wher they haue bene, whiche they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15035:15"/>
follow: I denie not, but among many there are founde, that without the example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, do ſtraunge things of themſelues, not accuſtomed any where: and if ſuch actes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> honeſt and not repugnant to reaſon, they are to be commended though the multitude mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like them: who eſtéeme that onely to be wel and wiſely done, which is moſt common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and moſt people vſe: counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payſing vertue and wiſdome, with ſmall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, ſuppoſing ſuch as gouerne themſelues contrarie to their order of life, to be fooles: not conſidering which gouernment is beſt. To eſchue this publike reproufe, the auncientes haue ſayd, we muſt liue according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Countrie that we are in, which is to be vnderſtanded only in outward geſture and indifferent cauſes. For they will vs not, if in what Countrey ſoeuer we be, is vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cuſtome contrarie to vertue or reaſon, to approue and allow the ſame. Therefore we deſire ſtil to folow others in their actions, as though vertue remayned in the vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples doings, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is nothing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſo ignorant, ſo blind, and ſo vndiſcrete, as the people: who without iudgement, wanting all conſideration, and cleane voyde of reaſon, do purſue and approue their firſt determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15035:15"/>
and that if their doings, orenterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes fal out well, it is fortune: euen as a blind man ſhoulde wander in a darke vnknowne place, none would ſay he did it by cleareneſſe of his ſight, but at aduenture. For this cauſe, the lawes haue forbidden ſeditious compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying and vnlawfull aſſemblies, for that the moſt part of men are euill, peruerſe, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to their appetites and fooliſh affections, ſo as the terrible and monſtrous méeting of the vulgar ſort, doe commonly conſpyre, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of miſchéenous matters. <hi>Cicero</hi> pleading for <hi>Cn. Plancus,</hi> was accuſed of publike bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, for that in the election of the <hi>Ediles,</hi> his parte was preferred before one named <hi>Lateranenſus,</hi> a man notable vertuous, and of an honourable houſe: after he had ſhewed in popular election, the fauour of the people to be more of value than the dignity of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which they regard not: there is (ſaith he) neither cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, iudgement, reaſon, or diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the people: and our predeceſſors were euer of this opinion, that the deuices, determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; deliberations of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon multitude ſhuld rather be diſſimuled tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alowed. Bring then c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuerſant in the world, and familiar in worldly cauſes, approuing the vulgar opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, we ſhall eaſily accuſtome our ſelues to doe that is euill. For ſo ſoone
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15035:16"/>
as the ſmal ſparks of vertue be extinguiſhed in vs, and that we abandon or leaue to folow the faſhion of the Court, we ſhall become ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert maſters in euil: ſo apt &amp; capable we are to learne it (as <hi>Iuuenal</hi> ſayth) <hi>Quoniam dociles imitandis Turpibus ac praais omnes ſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This cuſtome to do euil, and thus to liue, ſo chaungeth and altereth our nature, not knowing good from euill, as it makes vs nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to couet the one or ſhunne the other: we account good, and preferre to be the ſoueraine good, that which beſt pleaſeth vs, &amp; is alowed good in the world: and in the felicity &amp; delight of men, we repoſe and determin our vertue. For the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtue of man conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth not in that which is only good of itſelfe, folowing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Philoſophie: but in that which ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to them good, &amp; is no other than a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine maner of liuing, or rule in life. And ſince it is diuers, according to the diuerſitie of Countries &amp; people, as in times paſt were ſundry ſects of Philoſophers, we wil treat of that which is moſt allowed, &amp; embraced (for that it is more maſked and diſguiſed than the others) which is Courtly life. The knowlege wherof, we may aptly cal in theſe days Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie. And this I mind to treate of, bicauſe that they that know it &amp; can vſe it, are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wiſe men and Philoſophers.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15035:16"/>
               <head>The definition of this <hi>Philoſophie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr new and morall <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie</hi> may thus be defined: A certaine &amp; ſound iudgement, howe to liue according to the good grace and faſhion of the Court. I am ſure this definition cannot bée pleaſing to euery one: for ſome profeſſers of Artes, which peraduenture more ſubtiller &amp; according to the <hi>Stoikes</hi> maner, touch things néerer, will ſay vnto mée, that the ſame order of liuing can be nothing leſſe, or farther vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the propertie of <hi>Philoſophie:</hi> for all <hi>Philoſophie</hi> conſiſteth in the knowledge of ſecrete &amp; hidden cauſes, and in that which no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye can diſcerne. But to liue Courtly, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the maner of the Court, conſiſteth in certaine ſmall humanities, and chiefly in outward apparances: wherevnto I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that the <hi>minor</hi> is not true: for though a Courtier may bée knowen by his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance geſture, and behauiour (which is our <hi>Philoſopher)</hi> as they may all other kinde of people, yet the true ſcience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth not only in the ſame. But rather it is impoſſible for any to gouern themſelues ſo well, to haue a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15035:17"/>
Courtly grace &amp; entertainement, if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye vnderſtande not the opinions of the Court. For (as theyr maiſter <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth) all actions &amp; operations procéede of true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; knowledge: and how may wée be ſingular in that which we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not? None therfore ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a good Courtier, onleſſe he vnderſtand what pleaſeth beſt &amp; is moſt liked at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Court: &amp; to giue <hi>Beſo los manos,</hi> after the Spaniſhe maner, to embrace with lowe reuerence, and to make a braue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, with other ſuch like, ſuffiſeth not: as I may aptlie applie for example, oure mayſters of Artes, who haue mouths to kiſſe, armes to èmbrace, and faces to countenance, &amp; can do all this well: yet were it ſtraunge to ſée one of them in his old girded gowne furred with white, his burnt pantofles, &amp; his night cap of fréeſe, to fall on dauncing &amp; ſporting amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fayre Ladies. How he would courte it with them, how hee would pleaſe and entertaine them, &amp; how he would rauiſh their bartes or allure them? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neyther his wanton looke, or ſmiling cheare, his humble curteſie, nor lowe embracing, (though they would ſuffer it) would ſerue him amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted wiſe, or wel learned. And why ſo? Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are not wel pleaſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15035:17"/>
beſéeme not a man of iudgement and knowledge, too pleaſe ſuche companie. For if hée did, hée woulde bée otherwiſe apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and muſter in gallanter manner: hée woulde frame a courtlie countenance, and ſéeme gentle, modeſt and pleaſante, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſprightes to ſpeake and vnderſtand nothing but mery &amp; gladſome purpoſes. And thus finely furniſhed with his little Page in place of his poore &amp; ragged ſcholler, he might peraduenture bée welcome. Lette vs then mayneteyne and holde this for a <hi>maxime</hi> or principle, that to gouerne our ſelues accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Courte, wée oughte and muſte haue the true vnderſtanding of the opinions of the Courte, &amp; vertues of the ſame, whiche obtayned, will make vs in all our actions to be comelie, honeſt, and ventuouſe, and to bée eſteemed graue, wiſe, and ſounde of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: from the which proceedeth this <hi>Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum generale,</hi> generall comelineſſe, that <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaketh ſo much of in his Offices: &amp; ſayeth, that it may better be conceiued in imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than vttered by cunning: whiche wée maye nowe terme the good grace of euery one, whereof wée wyll treate more heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. So that yf anye woulde indeuer them ſelues to doe ſuche things, and wante
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15035:18"/>
the true knowledge hereof, they ſhall fayle of their purpoſe, while ſuppoſing to winne honor and praiſe, they may cauſe themſelues to bée derided of euery man, as is commonly ſeene in theſe rude youthes, &amp; ſkilleſſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Court, great companions &amp; woers of the Citie, Counterfaite Courtiers whiche ſimper it in outwarde ſhewe, making pretie mouthes, &amp; marching with a ſtalking pace like Cranes, ſpetting ouer their own ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſpeaking liſpingly, &amp; anſwering ſinging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with perfumed gloues vnder their girdels their buſkins pinkt &amp; cut, their ſhort clokes, their little cappes, their heare curled after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> maner of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> ſomtimes a little lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g locke turned vp like a pigs tayle betweene their te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples &amp; the eare: And in this attire, with a word or two of Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che, Italian, or Spaniſh, which they cary in their budgettes, they dare deuiſe with any noble perſon of the affayres of the realme, &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing with a maieſty, how the king hath ſhewed greate fauour to ſuch a gentleman. Of theſe it may be ſaide, as heretofore was ſaide of the Philoſopher, hée hath a fayre bearde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhaue him, &amp; take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all his wiſedome. So take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions theſe kind of habits or apparell which I haue deſcribed, and you ſhall finde them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15035:18"/>
beaſtes, doltes, loutes and clownes. But though ye do not, thoſe, whoſe eyes are of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable iudgement, can diſcerne them well ynough.</p>
               <p>AFter wée haue thus giuen the definition of our Philoſophie: &amp; ſhewed both the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument &amp; reaſons, we haue to call theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo defined Philoſophie: It ſeemeth very méete, to ſpeake of the effect therof, which is vertue. For the end of <hi>Morall Philoſophie,</hi> is grounded onely on vertue: wherevnto none can attaine, but by the meane of this ſcience. And I beleue without ſearching any further, or making ſo many diſtinctions of <hi>Genus &amp; Species,</hi> as the ouer ſcrupulous and curious haue doone, that in taking one parte of our former definition, wée haue the ſame of our vertue. The which by a certaine and ſhorte diuiſion, in forme of a deſcription wée ſhall plainelyer and better ſhewe hereafter. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is a manner of lyuing according too the manner of the Courte, and differeth from the Philoſophie of the Auncientes, in that their vertue (as I haue ſayde afore) is to liue according to the iuſtinct of Nature: and ours is too lyue according too the manner of the Courte. And euen as it was aunciently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15035:19"/>
that if wée followe Nature and doe no more than oure naturall reaſon ſheweth vs, wée ſhoulde neuer doe euill: ſo, if wée followe the manner and cuſtomes, in due and true order of the Courte, wée ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doe that is ſéemelye, good, and well. For who is ſo raſhe, fooliſhe, or madde, that wyll ſaye any thing is euylidoone, whiche is doone by a Gentleman Courtier, well inſtructed. Maye wée not then call them beaſts, and doltes, which are ignorant of the pryce and valewe of oure Courtly vertue? It makes me reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the old <hi>Atticque,</hi> who vnderſtoode not the phraſes of an eloquente Orator, when hée ſpake a woord moſt méete and well placed too the behoofe of the poore beaſte: hée ſcroned him for his labour. The propertie of ignorance is too brutiſhe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, who as they are not content with that they cannot doe or deuiſe any thing of themſelues: ſo will they not regarde or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme that for wel which the wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned do ſay. Héereof it is that <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaketh ſo much in his oration <hi>pro A. Cluen.</hi> nighe too the myddeſt. Therefore ſeeing the Courte and Courtlye countenance is the onely rule whereby and wherevpon wée muſte guyde and frame our life, it is not to bée maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15035:19"/>
at, if good wyttes wellborne, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous too attayne to this perfection of vertue. doe earneſtlye aſke, and diligentlye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre of commers and goers from and too the Courte for newes: What doe they? What ſaye they? What manner of lyuing is there nowe among them? What ſortes of apparell, what ſportes, what faſhyons newlye forged? who is beſte welcome, moſt regarded, and in greateſt eſtimation? who is moſt braue? who is the trimmeſt dauncer, the pleaſanteſt deuyſer, and the beſte vaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? what authors are moſte alowed, what bookes reade they, what ſongs carryeth the brute? And a thowſande other lyke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundes. For howe ſhoulde wée elſe nowe knowe the meane of lyuing with the good preceptes and doctrine of the auncient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers paſte, and chéefelie of thoſe that are not wrytten, or of ſuche whoſe bookes are partlye loſte, as <hi>Pythagoras, Socrates, Cratippus,</hi> and others, and of the Noble &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Romanes: if it were not had fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tellers of tales &amp; caryers of newes. Leaue of then to reproue our Engliſh men, &amp; to ſay, that it were requiſite and néedeful to place certaine perſons in highwaies, that ſhould haue none other occupation, but to report &amp; tell newes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15035:20"/>
too thoſe that paſſe by: why ſhoulde their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſire (not curioſitie) to vnderſtand newes, which I greatly allow, be any way reproued or touched? And euen as the good and famous lyues of oure elders, whoſe examples doo greatlye ſtirre vs vp to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, woulde bée profitable for vs, yf by wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wée ſhoulde knowe them, (whiche is the principall argumente whereby Cicero ſheweth the benefite and vtilitie of letters, in pleading for the Poet <hi>Archias)</hi> ſo howe coulde ſo manye wyſe and honeſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers of the Courte, ſerue too the example of thoſe that neuer ſawe them: were it not for the reporters and blaſers of newes? And further ſuche reportes encourageth, euen thoſe that are ſpoken of too indeuour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues too doe better: for the Philoſophye whereof wée treate, importeth not the ſame that the Auncientes doothe: who woulde haue vs, withoute any hope of honour too embrace and followe vertue for the loue of hir ſelfe: but that wée ſhoulde or oughte too liue vertuouſly, to the ende to obtayne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and reputation, as well too oure ſelues, as to oure poſteritie, whereof it is ſayde <hi>Virtutis merces gloria:</hi> Honour is the guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and rewarde of Vertue. And truelye
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15035:20"/>
I beléeue, if other teſtimonie might haue bin had of <hi>Ciceros</hi> conſcience (whome I name ſo oft for the excellencie of the man) than by his owne writings: we ſhould find, that in troth honor made him attempt and execute many things, eſpecially he aboue all the other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines: which it appeareth he could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither ſo couertly conceale, by this place laſt alledged. What ſhall I ſaye of poore <hi>Ouid,</hi> when he was in exile in that barbarous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Scythia</hi> neare the Sea coaſt? hauing there no companie that would commend him when he had made any verſes, as they dyd when he was at Rome in his brauerie and full of prche conceytes? he had there no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger courage to do any thing, for his pleaſant vayne lefte him, as he doth excellently wryte to Seuerus <hi>de Ponto.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Impetus ille ſacer, qui vatum pectoranutrit</l>
                  <l>Qui prius in nobis eſſe ſolebat, abest</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The heauenly force that fraughtes with ſtore</l>
                  <l>of skill, each Poets prudent hed</l>
                  <l>(VVhich homely harbor eft before</l>
                  <l>was wont with me to take) is fled.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>The reaſon hereof foloweth after.</head>
                  <l>Excitat auditor ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dium, laudataque virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Creſcit, &amp; immenſum gloriacalcar habet.</l>
                  <l>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cui recitem? &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15035:21"/>
                  <l>The eare to ſtudie ſturres,</l>
                  <l>Each vertue prayſed growes,</l>
                  <l>Each glorie gayneth ſpurres</l>
                  <l>As gayned glorie flowes.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Let vs conclude, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommoditie of true reporters and faithful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters of newes, is great, neceſſarie and profitable to good life. But to returne to oure purpoſe, the vertue whereof we ſpeake, is whollie ſet and placed in the court: euen as the ſame of the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cients is placed in nature: whiche we maye more better and perfitlier vnderſtande, if in follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the precepts and order of ſuch Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers as are leaſt ſcrupulous or preci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, we deuide it into foure hyndes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Wiſedome, Iuſtice, Magnanimiſte, and Temperance, whiche are the foure fountaines or ſprings from whence procéedeth the perfection of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. And though they be ſo wel lincked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that the one can not goe without the other (for who will cal any vertuous, be they neuer ſo profounde and wiſe, if they be not true and iuſt?) and that the four together and not one alone, make a man to be accounted wiſe: yet the diuiſion and particion is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither vnprofitable, to the ende that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> certayne diſpoſition ſo framed, we maye the eaſilyer iudge to what parte or place of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15035:21"/>
boneſtie euery action ought to be referred, to inſtructe the rude and learners. For in all ſciences, it ſufficeth not alone to vnderſtande the Arte: but alſo we ought to haue the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode to teach as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, <hi>de le gibus. Non fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſcire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> est, ſed quaedant est ars etiam docendi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> It is better therefore to ſpeake di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and by order of euery one of theſe ſeuerall kyndes (whereof vertue is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of an harmonie) than by vndiſcrete order or raſhe confuſion, to ſpeake generally of vertue.</p>
               <p>Yet before we enter into priuate or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular iudgement of vertue, and the better to findethe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into this pleaſant Garden, where groſſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that greate and fayre tree in whoſe top <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> is placed: it ſhall be verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we keepe one pathe, as vpon a planke or brooge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olde this for a principall poyute that followeth. The Auncientes among other preceptes of theyr Philoſophie: the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſilyer to ſet foorth and make knowne their vertue, would at the beginning giue this for a maxime, <hi>Noſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ipſum: <hi>knowe thy ſelfe,</hi>
                  </hi> affirming, that if by this meane a man once knewe himſelfe, the ſhoulde finde ſomething in him lyke to the Goddes: the which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation with the deitie, ought to bridle hym
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15035:22"/>
with ſhame from doing euill, and pricke him forward to do well. And there is in this ſhort ſentence, and vnder theſe two wordes, much matter of great efficacie and force: for the better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wherof, I wil diſcharge myſelfe by <hi>Cicero,</hi> in the end of his firſt boke of lawes. And whereas ours Philoſophie ſprings from an other fountaine than theirs whiche procéedeth onely out of nature, and oures of the contentmente and pleaſure of men: So are the wayes ſundry to fynde the diuerſitie of theſe two. I thinke it good ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that to come to this perfection of our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in ſtead of knowing ourſelues, we ought to ſée and knowe the worlde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for after a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite iudgement of the whole, we ſhall the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtand one part. And when we haue the knowledge of ſundrie faſhions of liuing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the contrarietie of ſome, and the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſitie of others, it giueth an intire and true vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this: and further, amongſt all other the excellencie of this will ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mightily draw, and ſo ſtrongly allure good wittes and gentle courages, that all other orders of life l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t and ſhaken off, they only will followe this, which is the faſhions of the Court. But to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde it may be vnderſtanded, what I call ſeeing of the world, it is not to mounte on horſeback<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15035:22"/>
and ryde from hence to <hi>Paris,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> to Mounte <hi>Synay,</hi> from Mount <hi>Synay</hi> to ſeeke S. <hi>Patrikes</hi> Purgatorie, and from thence to the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Canibales.</hi> For to ſée the worlde, is not to ſée many buildings or countries, or to paſſe ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie Seas, though it be ſome what to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and that by it maye partly be knowne the ſame I ſpeake of: yet I meane, ſéeing of the world is to vnderſtande the cuſtome, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and maners of ſundrie nations, wyth their properties and faculties, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation they vſe one to the other. And thus may we do and not trauel far for it, as béeing in ſome famous and notable Citie (wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is great reſorte of diuers ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngers) we may make a perfit impreſſion in our myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of that we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſée, and ſometimes, it is otherwiſe attayned vnto by reading in bookes. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e proofe whereof is perceiued by ſundrie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome haue paſt moſte part of the worlde, and muſtred in all the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pes that haue bin in many yeares, they an accounted to vs the platfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of Caſtles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arts, and Churches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſituation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iption of countries, and other notable things, as much as is poſſible to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and as the eye maye at any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: others that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s their whole
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15035:23"/>
life time remaynes at the Courte, at <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> at <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nice,</hi> at <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome,</hi> at <hi>Lyons,</hi> at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntwery,</hi> and ſuche frequented Cities, celebrated with meſt reſorte of people: are notwithſtanding very beaſtes, and haue no more knowledge than a poore peaſant, whiche neuer was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of the ſight of his pariſhe ſteeple, ſauing that they can playe on the bytte a litle better, and march more delicately and ſtately. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, for that the one ſorte are ſo abaſhed &amp; aſtonied at the ſuddaine change of thoſe new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eities and rare deuiſes they ſee in ſtraunge countries, which ſeemes to alter in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the iudgement of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rightes is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo troubled, as it cannot conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of any thing right: where at they are ſo lightly moued, as they reſemble braineleſſe fooles, that run ſo faſt through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reat they regard not what they ſée, where they are, nor what place it is they be in. And the others are ſo accuſtomed with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne only thing, that this cuſtome and familiarity of daily ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, doth ſo weary &amp; dull their minds, that they take no hée de of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or accounting more of it any way at all, than of that they neuer ſaw, Hereof it is, that Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſpeaketh ſo much in the. 11. booke <hi>de Natura Deoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> giuing this reaſon, why the <hi>Atheiſtes</hi> did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15035:23"/>
not acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there was but one God by his works, ſeeing the heauens, the planets &amp; ſtars, the earth, the elementes, &amp; other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes of his, ſaying: <hi>Sed aſsiduitate quotidiana &amp; conſuetudine oculorum aſſueſcunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi, neque admirantur, neque requirunt rationes earum rerum, quas ſemper viderunt, perinde quaſi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas ipſa nos magis, quam magnitudo reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debeat ad exquirendas cauſas excitare.</hi> Which is to ſay: that our ſenſes are ſo dull and glutted, with that our eyes doe daily ſee and beholde, as it is no maruell to vs, neither doe we conſider howe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes to paſſe, or howe it was made, nor who is the cauſe, as thoughe the rareneſſe rather than the greatneſſe or excellencie of anye thing ſhoulde make vs the more to wonder. It is then the mynde and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man onely, that ſeeth and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth any thing in his perfit kinde: the which we ſhould dayly ſturre vp, and ſo accuſtome with good purpoſes, that it decaye or ruſte not in vs: wherby ſéeing and diſcerning with iudgement the maners &amp; liuing of all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, we maye the eaſilier and truelyer knows ours: And by the ſame vnderſtanding come to the perfection of our vertue. For the good credite and praiſe whereof, I may boldly ſay and affirme, that there is no eaſier meane,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15035:24"/>
nor pleaſanter manner of liuing than in dure Philoſophie: As for the world paſt I liſt not to meddle withall, nor ſearch how the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philoſophers (whoſe doctrine ſerues litle to our purpoſe) found or liked it in their days. But ſure I am, that time hathe euer ſince, brought his alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as touching death the diſſoluer of their Philoſophie, to expell the feare of him, they haue ſpoken marual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, and in moſt of their workes haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the deſpiſing of death vnto vs: yet in my opynion it coulde not but greatly gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them: for the ground and foundation of theyr profeſſion, whiche is nature, was cleane put out and cut off by it. I reporte to Moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who viewed all that paſt the floud <hi>Acheron</hi> to bell: and ſawe none but that baſhed and were aſtonied in the going in, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Diogenes,</hi> which did nothing but ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffs and ieſt at all things: who as he euer conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned life, ſo was he neuer ſeene fearefull of death at any time. Moſt true it is that <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> farre off, had a good courage and ſéemed to deſpiſe it, but when he came to the wicke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he chaunged coloure as well as others. Let vs nowe proceede to the purpoſe, and ſpeake of our vertue in hir ſeuerall kynds by order, without confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15035:24"/>
               <head>Of Prudence or wiſdome.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His noble <hi>Troy</hi> wherein (as I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aide) our vertue is ſeated, hath foure armes or branches, wherby we muſt aſcend &amp; elimb vp vnto hir: the firſt principal &amp; chief braunch we cal Prudence, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in a ſkilful iudgement and knowledge of true things. For it is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poſſible that by our daily doings, we can wel pleaſe the world, if we know not throughly what we do. From this knowledge proceedes the vnderſtanding of all Artes and liberall Sciences, whereby we become right Courtiers: As of Muſicke, the playing on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone, the Harpe, the Corne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the Flute, the Virginals, the Viall, and other ſweete muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal inſtruments Alſo to daunce all maner of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: as the double &amp; ſimple bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>owe</hi> and <hi>Champanay,</hi> the ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e daunce, the Almayne, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>allyard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and infinit others, The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to compoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, Poſtes, pleaſant purpoſes, Songs, So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e to, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orous Lame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, verſe, or ryme, very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ragie all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the languiſhing pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a ſeruant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and euill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>warded of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15035:25"/>
Further, it is ſingular good, to haue ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſprinckled iudgement in the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and practizes of all the liberall ſciences, chapt vp in hot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hpot togither, out of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we may ſtill help ourſelues in talke, with apte deuiſes at aſſayes, to haue ſubſtance and matter to treate of, and encounter with all maner of things, and no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Alſo to haue ſtore of hiſtories, to paſſe the time méet for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny company, and with the more aſſured cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to couche our credite, it ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to enterlace our diſcourſes with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſuddaine lyes and inuentions of oure owne forging. Likewiſe the knowledge of diuers and ſundry languages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the ſpaniſh, the Frenche, the Italian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Dutche, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: to the ende that in all theſe ſeuerall tongues, we may ſalute, reioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, wonder a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, exclayme vpon, diſdayne, ſk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te whome we will. The knowledge of Fence, of va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting, of Tennis, of dauncing, and other ſportes of exerciſe: And ſome vnderſtanding of the ſtate and affayres of the Realm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as of warres, of practizes, of marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and howe we maye honeſtly robb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, deceyue, and make our beſt profite. And withall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertayne other ſmall pettie practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes and traffiques, that are vſed in the world,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15035:25"/>
in which euery one cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts to excell, for the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able conſideration that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of it. On the contrarie, ſuch as are ignoraunt in theſe faculties, and will not endeuer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to haue ſome ſmacke or ſmell in euery one of them, are beaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, doltes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alues. And for that Vertue is the meane betwéene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo bites, as it is commonly in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntrarie oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences: when the two extremities are knowne, the midſt is eaſily founde, which is our vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Prudence then (as we haue ſaid) is the perfite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath way and iudgement to all the artes afore ſpoken of, wherin is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded, that I meaſure this perfection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ure, but reputation of the Court. And he, who is ſo throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the ſciences, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e knoweth thereby howe to aduaunce his credite and honour, is po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te, and wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to be called wife. But this meane (that I ſpeake of) is ſo hard to kéep, that there are few which declyne not to the one ſide or the other. Some beléeuing wel of them ſelues, that they are ſingular in theſe arts, and yet want the true tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to beginne, weigh things lightly, regarding neither place time, nor counſel: whervpon they are accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wilful &amp; ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Others that would be eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more graue &amp; ſage th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the reſt, do muſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15035:26"/>
&amp; breake their braynes with trifling folli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s which ſerue to no purpoſe, and there aboutes ſpende ineſtimable paine &amp; time: &amp; theſe are too curious. Take therefore the meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene both, and you ſhall come to the true and entire knowledge of thinges honeſt and neceſſarie: and ſo you haue oure vertue. From temeritie and raſhneſſe it is not néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to diſuade any by morall reaſons: for there are ſo manye infected with this follie, and their wilfulneſſe winnes them ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in the worlde, as they are noted and ſcoffed at of all men: and I beleeue the wife beware by them ſince they knowe the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Walke one night through <hi>Paris,</hi> and you ſhall finde a compani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of yong gallants, ſome braue and in good order, and others ſmothly combed for the purpoſe, courting and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Ladies: and for that they are ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull howe the knowledge of this Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie maye bring them into their miſtres fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our, beléeue of themſelues to be paſſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and ſingular good players on the Lute and Gitterne, and do nightly walke the ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes before their louers gates, tearing the poor ſtrings of their inſtrumentes, as it were in deſpite of <hi>Mercurie.</hi> Their miſtreſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylde nature (ſome ſuche there are) that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15035:26"/>
they account this the greateſt glorie &amp; moſt delight in the world, to heare how their amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſeruantes, with ſundrie ſorts of muſicke preſent their louing obedience. As it is ſayde of a Dame in <hi>Rhoane,</hi> who to trye the loyaltie of hir Louer, made a croſſe with chaulke on hir chamber doore, and enioyned him pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, nightly to come and kyſſe it, who was ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout that he thought it ſacriledge to breake ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e with his miſtres: till ſome merie mate ſpying and pitying his inceſſant paine, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his deuotion, mending the workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of this relique with ſuch ſupple ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the poore penitent, hauing bothe his noſe and lippes par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell gilt withall, gaue ouer his Pilgrimage for euer. So theſe pigions holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus by the noſe, and fed peraduenture with a farewell from ſome kynde Miſtreſſe, who knowes howe to continue their follie: doe nowe and then méete with odde remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As when their ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt hapneth to be wher dwelleth ſome braue philoſopher of the court, whoſe delicate eares cannot indure ſo great iuiurie done to <hi>Orpheus,</hi> by their diſordred ſer a pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g and crouding, do bliſſe them out at their windows with a pifpet, perfuming both the players and their inſtrumentes, in ſuche ſwéete maner, as the gallantes are not heard
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15035:27"/>
of in a moneth after. Some other ſuppoſing themſelues perfit dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cers, for that they haue heard ſay it is an excellent grace not to ſéeme to haue care or to thinke of their daunce, do in dauncing before noble damſels, frame their countenance with a counterfet modeſtie, and letting their cape ſlip off the one ſhoulder in ſhewe their gay ierkins or dublets, kéeping euer this good mean, that it may be ſuppoſed they deliuer their trippes and trickes eaſily, without labour or regarde of theyr daunce, by little and little lets it fall off on the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber floure: And thus the gallants glorying in their own ſhadowes, tread their two ſimples with a double tricke, and beleeue they haue done ſingular lywell, I leaue to common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, howe the lookers on doe laugh at it. Another poore foole, yet a Gentleman of coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce, who thinkes him ſelfe learned in languages, trauelling by the way, and taking vp his lodging where lieth a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, for that he wil ſéem to haue language, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes him with <hi>Bonne iourne,</hi> although it be v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late: the Italian ſuppoſing him in a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerie to pronounce <hi>Bougeronne,</hi> without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding any more, draweth out his r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pler: our mynion mated to ſée this ſuddaine furie, not knowing the cauſe, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to defende himſelfe: &amp; ſo they are doth in danger the one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15035:27"/>
to maime or marre the other vpon this fond &amp; fooliſh quarell. Poore ſoules haue pacience. &amp; conſider howe your ignorance makes you no better than brute beaſtes. And if I durſt ſpeake of Orators, who ſuppoſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to haue double iudgements in al maner of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, for one litle word that they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to be vnderſtand and eloquently vtter, being of ſmall conſequence, will trauell ſo far about for it, that ſome of them are neuer able to come to their matter againe. And touching Aduocates and lawyers, who will ſeem with their ſtore of law to carie al before them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d neither y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> point, but, nor mark of the cauſe wherevnto they ſhould tend their talk: which y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good ſcholemaſter <hi>Quintilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> doth declare: for after (ſaith he) they haue graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a long preface pleaded in latine and french iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled togither, their clients caſe, in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> end <hi>Parturiunt mentes. &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>Huge moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines trauell with yong, and at length bring forth a ſillie Mouſe.</hi> They open the principall places, &amp; after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the laws, doctors, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nons togither: yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefie that part moſt which is leaſt aſſaulted, &amp; ſuddenly ſomtimes ouerthrow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſius maior</hi> a <hi>Romane,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> painteth ſo gallantly pleading for <hi>Cluencus,</hi> was a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doer herein.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15035:28"/>None can ſufficiently declare the great iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and other inconueniences that chanceth in enterpriſes of importance, as in the feates of warre and pollicie, in marchandiſe, in phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, and diuinitie it ſelfe, through this raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for example, raſhe Tylers ofte breake their owne neckes. And to conclude, there are ſo many examples of raſhe, braineſicke, and headſtrong people, that their vice is ſo noted, as it néedes no more reproofe. The remedie to avoyde the falling into the faulte of raſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is to conſider of all cauſes not ſuddenly, but with diſcretion, deliberation, and good councell.</p>
               <p>The other vice and extremitie of <hi>Prudence,</hi> is Curioſitie (as we haue ſayde afore) whiche is no leſſe daungerous than this laſt we haue treated of, yet is it much more painefull: for the raſhe man executes his determinations and purpoſes without ſtudie or iudgement, the curious man with great circumſtaunce tormentes himſelfe daye and night, and both of like ſubſtance and profit. The great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher <hi>Plutarch</hi> in a certaine treatiſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>he defineth what Curioſitie is: compareth the curious man to a houſholder a very euill huſbande, who hath euer his noſe out at his windowe, viewing and noting the doings
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15035:28"/>
and gouernment of other men, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding nor hauing eye to his own familie, whoſe ſeruantes and varlettesin the meane tyme doe ſpoyle and robbe him within his doores. That man is double blinde in hys owne euill, that killeth himſelfe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers rares, trauelles, and toyles: and yet his buſyneſſe no whit the ſooner doone. Wée wyll call him Curious in oure Courtlye Philoſophie, that breaks his braines in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſecretes of ſuche Artes and Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as ſerue too no purpoſe for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of oure lyfe according too vertue, that is too ſaye, according too the manner of the Courte. Lette vs then conſider howe farre ſuche a one ſwarueth from Prudence or wiſedome: yet there are manye in theſe dayes that treade the ſteppes of the auncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sages, and thereby ſéeke too attayne to this true and perfect vertue (as they call it) whiche is lodged ſo hyghlie and ſtatelie, and in a place ſo harde and daungerous to come too. You ſhall ſée ſome ſuche curiouſe men in the Courte, ſolemne, ſadde, and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike, that will not eate but at preſcribed houres, they will not ſpeake but when it pleaſeth them, they wyll not laughe for the Pope, nor bée ſubiect too anye Prince or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15035:29"/>
Lorde, bée hée neuer ſo greate: euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; miſliking of that which others do: and to conclude, they are not pleaſante to anye perſon. To what ende or purpoſe ſerueth this greate curioſitie, oneleſſe it gyueth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion too the worlde, too call them precyſe fooles and ſeruants to <hi>Signour Monarche?</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall they with their gloſed hypocriſie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the fauour and good reputation of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Gentlemen and ciuil Courtiers? neuer. If another <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſhould come amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, with his ſtaffe and his wallet, blowing and ſupping his wortes in his tunne, would not the Pages roll him vp and downe? But if he were a <hi>Minippus,</hi> or Fryer Iohn of Saincte Anthonies order, they woulde prayſe him better. There are to be found infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers verye curiouſe in thouſandes of ſmall follies, moſt vnprofitable and ſeruing to no purpoſe, &amp; yet will ſéeme great wiſe men &amp; of ſingular knowledge: as prognoſticators, Southſayers, Magiciens, and Alkumiſtes, notwithſtanding theſe laſte haue béene of late, and yet are welcome and well allowed of ſome for the time. But I beléeue their credit will not haue place long. It ſuffiſeth to knowe ſo muche of their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iences, as may ſerue too paſſe pleaſante diſcourſes among
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15035:29"/>
companie, and no more. For the reſte, it is nothing to our vertue, but rather hindreth and letteth from attayning the true &amp; honeſt meane that ſhould bring vs to the perfection therof. And thus you haue the ſumme of that whiche in oure Philoſophie is called Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or Wiſedome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>IVſtice being next and aduauncing hir ſelf in hir order, is the ſame vnto the whiche we muſt referre all our other concluſions, &amp; without the which the whol hath no part in vertue. For to what end or purpoſe doth the knowledge of any art or ſcience profit vs, if the ſame be learned onely for fraude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte? How may wée iuſtly call or accompte any of a noble harte and inuincible minde, able too frounte all fortunes, if hée em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy and indeuoure himſelfe to harme and iniurie others? Are not modeſte men and thoſe that dawnte their appetites, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due their affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to reaſon, worthy to be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iuſte? without Iuſtice no vertue could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, ſtand, or ſhould be ſupported Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to take greate paine, &amp; employ all our ſtudies too the true knowledge of hir.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15035:30"/>
And for that ſhe is of ſo mighty a maieſty as hir braunches cannot in bréefe definition bée co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, we wil in ſome ſort deſcribe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I am not altogither ignorant that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vulgare opinion of Iuſtice is a ſure &amp; perfect mind, to giue and do to euery man, that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto him: which truly is méete &amp; very requiſite. But ſince it ſéemeth vnto mée, either that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth much more, or elſe that it ought not (which belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs vnto it) to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſo generally, as the ſame ſhall néede more expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or explication tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuſtice hir ſelfe, I meane not to vſe it for a definition. For a beginning or principle it is a true maxime, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayeth, &amp; to be conſidered of, in the whole deduction of Iuſtice: That it is very good, not to iniury or wrong any. &amp; I thinke for the perfect acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment of this vertue, it ſuffiſeth not onely to iniury no perſon (as we will ſhew herafter) but we muſt alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor our ſelues to doe good to others: yet muſt we not vnderſtande, that in dooing no good where wée ought, though wée take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from him that is his, we do him wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: that were a ſuttell ſuppoſer, &amp; ſuche captious opinions are damnable. For we ſay not that to leaue pleaſuring of him whome wée very wel might pleaſure, is doing him any wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15035:30"/>
The Iuſtice wherof we write, may be diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though hardly, into <hi>Legal &amp; Moral:</hi> whoſe difference cannot without greate difficultie be knowne, for the néerneſſe of affinitie that is betwéene them, onleſſe we make ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, and treate of them ſeuerallye, to the ende it may bée diſcerned wherein they bée contrary, and wherin they agrée. All Iuſtice be it <hi>Legall or Moral,</hi> is diuided in two kinds: wherof the one propertie or kind is <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue,</hi> &amp; the other <hi>Diſtributiue:</hi> And I beléeue in my opinion, that out of this laſt <hi>Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, Cicero</hi> hath drawen liberalitie, which he makes &amp; affirmes to be one part or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Iuſtice, in his offices. Vnder theſe two kinds of Iuſtice, is confirmed, included, &amp; conſiſteth the whole actes &amp; doings in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mutuall ſociety of mans life. This is the ſame vertue that is ſayd to be the theater or place of humaine fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, vnder the which all people are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; ioyned one with the other, &amp; by the whiche euery one is warned from deuiding &amp; ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aſunder out of this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Notwithſtanding, after the time that the good diſpoſition and affection of men, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding onely of nature, was ouerthrowen and corrupted (as I haue ſayde at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) and that the Goddeſſe <hi>Aſtrea</hi> had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15035:31"/>
lefte the worlde, for that mankind began to deuide, ſcatter, and leaue the one the other (as <hi>Ouide</hi> doth excellently deſcribe in his <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis</hi>) and that this ſocietie and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panying of men loſt familiar felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, cleane contrarie to the will and intent of him that placed them héere: It hath bene and is needefull to giue them reynes, &amp; bits, to bridle, bynde, hold in, and entertaine them togither: which are the lawes Ciuill, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſuch men as at the firſt of their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall accorde, were good, iuſte, and loyall, are now conſtrayned to follow Iuſtice, not hir ſelfe, for ſhee hath lefte and forſaken the earthe, but one ſo like hir as maye bée. And thoſe that lyue and gouerne themſelues in ſuche orderly ſorte, as the lawes cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, nor any way touch them, wée ſay, to haue in them Iuſtice Legall: the which howe muche it is different from this firſte Iuſtice, whiche was before the gyuing and conſtituting of lawes, and that whiche is the ſame of the Auncient Philoſophers, in whoſe place oures is ſuccéeded, I leaue for this tyme too thinke of. Notwithſtanding I may ſaye thus muche, that the lawes Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill forbidde all offices, ſo farre onely as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15035:31"/>
they are borne, nouriſhed, and raigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men. But the Philoſophers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde all that they imagine in their mynds too bee contrarye too reaſon: whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes are ouer ſtrayghte and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous. This argumente is Ciceros (and therefore I will not ſéeme too deceyue him) in his Offices, where hée ſayeth: <hi>Aliter le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, aliter Philoſophi tollunt astutias: Leges, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenusmanus tenere poſſunt, Philoſophi, quatenus ratione &amp; intelligentia.</hi> Nowe further to oure purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Justice Legall, and of the Lawes Ciuill.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Egall</hi> Iuſtice, commeth of obſeruing the ciuill lawes, the keepers where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are called iuſte, and good: whiche hathe béene heeretoofore diuyded in <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatiue</hi> and <hi>Diſtributiue:</hi> wherein wée haue followed the opinion of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes, and alſo of <hi>Melancton,</hi> that Noble perſonage and beſte Philoſopher in oure tyme, as appeareth in one Epitome, whiche hée made of <hi>Morall Philoſophie,</hi> whiche notwithſtanding is contrary to this.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15035:32"/>
In this diuiſion is compriſed all that oure Counſellers and lawe makers haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: whoſe volumes, ſtudies, trauelles, and workes beeing gathered togither, haue made an entyer and perfect bodye: yet there haue bene many good doctors, that haue written ſundry matters, which ſmell neither of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatiue</hi> nor <hi>Diſtributiue.</hi> The <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue</hi> conſyſteth in cauſes touching con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes, titles, obligations, and actions: and conſequently in the right of any, too knowe who vſeth or enioyeth that hée hath rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or no: who may contract or bargayne, and wherefore wee may contract or no: Of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes, ſome are voluntarie, as buying, ſelling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ring, lending, gyuing, and others, of the which doth alſo procéede ſuppoſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes, whence commeth the ryghte of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. The others are compelled or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned: as all crymes and offences: ſo that moſte part of the Ciuill lawes are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in <hi>Commutatiue.</hi> And it is called <hi>Commutatiue,</hi> for that the firſte kinde of contracting and bargayning, whiche was then in cuſtome and vſage, was com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or exchaunge: For at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, before this poyſened infection of monie was forged, the good people of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15035:32"/>
worlde did chaunge that which they might ſpare, for that they wanted, (and as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſayth) there was no talke of buying nor ſelling, for the price and eſtimation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that grew by the cuſtomable encreaſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracting &amp; bargayning was not yet knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them: but after they had entred the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayles of the earth, and broken vp the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of their firſt mother, and that this thrice miſchieuous, inſaciable, execrable, and grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die famine of Golde and Siluer had aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vanquiſhed the harts of men, ſtraight way was found the glutted gaine of practiſe by trafficke, that exchaunge, permutation, &amp; election, had no more place among them: for there was nothing ſo worthie, holy, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or religious, that coulde then ſaue it ſelfe from the deuouring hurlepitte of greedie gayners.</p>
               <p>The other part of Iuſtice legall, is <hi>Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butiue,</hi> ſo called, for that it conſiſteth in diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting of honors, dignities, magiſtrateſhips, perſonages, offices benefices, immunities, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions, priuileges, franchiſes, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and of all other profites beſtowed on perſons worthie and well deſeruing in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſes: and alſo, the inſtitution howe ſuch people ſhould gouerne and beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15035:33"/>
in theſe eſtates and dignities. The which <hi>Diſtributiue,</hi> for that it is no other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rewarde of vertue, I eſteeme to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſo great commendation and prayſe, as nothing more, and therefore at this time wil touche it no further, but repoſe my ſelfe on that whiche the noble Orator <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> hath ſayde, in the Oration he made of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie agaynſt <hi>Leptinus,</hi> (who would haue diſanulled and taken it away:) where he hath ſo ſagely and profoundly ſet it out, and with ſuch wiſe and graue modeſtie ſhewed howe we ſhoulde recompence and regarde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie perſons and well deſeruers. And I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of the opinions, doe beſt allow of this: for it is (ſayeth he) a moſt fayre and commendable thing, not by flatterie or fraud, nor by reproch and tyrannie: but rightly and iuſtly, with our companions, familiars and like, in the lawes and the Citie, to ſhewe our ſelues among others to haue deſerued ſome dignitie: which eſtimation and credit if you take away, take alſo away your Common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth, for ſo will it be without gouerners &amp; gouernment. Thus haue you of the lawes Ciuill and Legall iuſtice, ſo much as ſerueth to our purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15035:33"/>
               <head>Of morall Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr iuſtice, wherby we muſt attaine to our vertue, that is to ſay, to be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome and well liked euery where, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wiſe, and good liuers, according to the maner of the Court, is much otherwyſe than the ſame we haue yet ſpoken of: as in ſome places, alowing more liberty, &amp; in ſome other more ſtrictneſſe and ſcrupulouſneſſe. And for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it doth extende further than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues (as we haue ſaide afore) ſo much is it the harder to ſhewe and name hir extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: wherin I can ſay no more, but affirm that whatſoeuer is not done according to our vertue, how, in what ſort, or whoſe act ſoeuer it be, is no other than manifeſt wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie. And to ſpeake of <hi>Commutatiue,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning contractes &amp; bargayning one with an other: this muſt euer be the principle or max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime, that we ought not to abuſe or wrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: yet by this is to be vnderſtanded if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie be not couered, or hild with ſome ſhew, or likelihood of reaſon (for we are not accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to conſider of cauſes ſo neare) as what he is, or whether he be honeſt or no, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away or withholdeth the goodes of an other: For it is not onelye ſufferable in bargaynyng, in buying, and ſellyng, for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15035:34"/>
euery man to make his moſt profite, be it by fraude or otherwiſe, but alſo verie commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. For (the Lawyers ſay) <hi>Licet contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentibus, inuicem ſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cipere. <hi>It is lawfull in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſellers, and marchantes, one to deceyue the other.</hi>
                  </hi> Is not that man worthie then to bée noted an Idiot, and to be baniſhed a common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth, who hath apt occaſion to deceyue or beguile his companion and mate by any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meane, and will not do it? he learneth it not by our Philoſophie, nor by the Court. We holde this generally as a great argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our vertue: that it is tollerable to beguile, filch, and cogge, and do the worſt we can, ſo that neither lawe, Iudge, nor iuſtice may touch or catch holde of vs for it. <hi>Nemini enim facit iniuriam, qui ſuo iure vtitur. <hi>He that makes the beſt of his owne, and mainteynes his owne right, doth wrong to none.</hi>
                  </hi> And this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tert to mainteine our owne right, we giue as a licence to do all things: wherein thoſe that are moſt ſubtile, craftie and ouer-reaching, are the beſt allowed and moſte eſtéemed of. Of whom it is ſayde, if they owe any thing they will pay it, and if any owe them, they will likewiſe looke to be well payed. And touching ſtryfes, contentions and offences: they are accuſtomed with this deſtinction to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15035:34"/>
be defined. Such as blade out their brawles manfully by armes, (whatſoeuer they be, or the cauſe they fight for) are not only to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, but rather to be commended: for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly thoſe that mainteyne their matters by the ſworde, either defend their perſons, or their honour, or they are prouoked and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreyned vnto it, ſo that they haue euer ſuche pretectes, or likely cloakes, vnder which the truth of their faultes and contentions lyeth hidden, and is couched ſo cunningly, that wée ſée them not: alſo we neuer regarde but the ſuperficial part of any thing, and that which ſheweth it ſelfe vnto vs. As for other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as robberies, ciuil iniuries, and ſuch like priuate faultes, they are much more repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; condemned than the reſt, for that they haue not theſe foreſayde cloakes and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhadowes, without the which, all crymes and offences are more damnable, by oure Philoſophie, than by the lawes: For Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers euer deſired a iuſtice more ſtrict, and a life more iuſt, than the Lawes do: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Gentlemen, Courtiers, and others of the Court, are not content with a preſcribed life, according to the Ciuill lawe: But they will yet adde thereto more. For an euill doer or guiltie perſone, at the leaſt fault that hée
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15035:35"/>
committeth, toucheth the honour of him that is offended, which is in theſe dayes the moſt odious and hatefulleſt offence that may bée. For none can ſo ſlenderly harme or hurte the honour of a Gentleman or Courtier, but the combate muſt ſtraite be chalenged for want of further proufe, ſo that for giuing of one lie, it is permitted lawfull and iuſt to kill a man: for the reproufe of vanitie, and the lye, is the greateſt ſcarre and mayme, that they maye giue to oure honour. Whereby it appeares what eſtimation we haue of our honour: ſéeing we are allowed as well to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende oure honour, as the auncientes and lawes themſelues haue allowed vs to defend our lyues, and not without reaſon: for honor and reputation is the finall concluſion of our vertue, without the whiche our vertue were of no value. All other offences therefore are lightlyer regarded of vs, than of the Lawes, by reaſon of their cunning coueryngs, and pretie pretertes, whereof I haue ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: except our reputation be touched, for in that cryme wée are nearer gréeued than at any other, wherein I muſte néedes ſay the Lawes haue béene too fauourable. For too knowe what things they are that doe ſtayne our honour, they may better bée thought off
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15035:35"/>
than ſpoken: yet I will ſay thus muche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſſe any further, that touching loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in worde, or humanitie in déede towarde oure equalles or inferi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs, it is nothing ſo requiſite in our iuſtice as in the Auncientes, where vppon they made theyr fyrſt and firme foundation: for it ſufficeth vs to holde and kéepe oure worde ſo farre as the Iudge and Lawe may compell vs to perfourme it. But to promiſe withoute the compaſſe and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of action, is no other than a brauerie, in well promiſing: wherevnto is applyed the common Preuerbe, that the promiſe of a Gentleman is holy water of the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſeconde part of Iuſtice which is Diſtributiue, and of Liberalitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He other part of our Iuſtice is <hi>Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butiue,</hi> which <hi>Cice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> properly calleth liberalitie, (and reaſon good:) for what elſe is liberalitie, than the beſtowing &amp; diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting of honors and goods to well deſeruing perſons? wherin the aunetents did flouriſh, &amp; made famous their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthes: &amp; ſurely in theſe days, I know no vertue ſo agréeable to our Philoſophie, as this ſame. For (as I
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15035:36"/>
haue often ſayde) the ſumme of our ſcience, and ende of our vertue hir ſelfe, is the glorie and reputation of anye man: and he which deſireth it, and ſéeketh it, is worthily accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wiſe, but he that hath it may be renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the happyeſt man in this worlde, who ſhal likewiſe liue for euer here in this world. On the contrarie, they that are careleſſe, and account not what is ſayde of them, are to be thought eyther blockiſh or careleſſe. <hi>Pithago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> letter could not in theſe dayes helpe vs to this happineſſe: neyther néedes <hi>Seneca</hi> now to breake our br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynes any more with this ſong,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Illi mors gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is incubat,</l>
                  <l>Qui notus nimis omnibus,</l>
                  <l>Ignotus moritur ſibi.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhom all men tooto well doe know,</l>
                  <l>a heauie ende he makes:</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe yet to himſelfe vnknowne</l>
                  <l>this preſent life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orſakes.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>For if we be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ous and knowne, wée cannot attain to the perfection of our vertue: as <hi>Claudian</hi> ſheweth in his Countrie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and this gallant <hi>Ouid,</hi> that became ſo wiſe, after he had receyued correction. <hi>Crede mibi, bene quilatuit, bene vixit, &amp; intia Fortunam debet quiſque manereſuam.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15035:36"/>
                  <l>Beleeue me who ſo liues within</l>
                  <l>his reach, he liueth well:</l>
                  <l>For eche man ought within the bondes</l>
                  <l>of his owne hap to dwell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>And further.</head>
                  <l>Viue ſine inuidia, moleſque inglorius annos</l>
                  <l>Exige, amicitias &amp; tibi iunge pares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seeke life that enuie lackes</l>
                  <l>Mixt landleſſe life with pleaſant yeeres,</l>
                  <l>No friendſhip ioyne with lackes,</l>
                  <l>Yet friendſhip frame, but with thy peeres.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>I leaue therfore this to thoſe that are ſo déep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plunged in wiſedome, who agrée all with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon voyce, ſaying that they are moſt ſage and wiſe, which ſhew themſelues moſt meeke and humble: for it is directly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and contrarye to oure Courtly vertue. Then ſince honour is the marke whereat we all ſhoulde tende our deſire: is there any readier meane to good reputation, than by liberalitie to deſtribute oure treaſure too all the worlde: to ſhewe pleaſure to all that come: to be fauourable and curteous to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one: to reſcue ſome from the Prouoſt and Marſhals, &amp; to frée others from being Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaues: &amp; to kéep &amp; feed v. or vj. pore knaues as rauening as woolues: to make feaſts, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes, &amp; bankets with open houſe? no truly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15035:37"/>
               <head>Of liberalitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His vertue conſiſteth in the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of three things in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall goods, and this belongeth to great Lords. In reuerences and honor, and that is the duetie of inferiour companions: and in ſpirituall gifts, which is the office of thoſe that are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As touching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſt, the principle which we ought to regarde, is to vſe no liberalitie, but to ſuch as deſerue it: by whoſe meanes wée may bée accounted Philoſophers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Court, and worthie of this reputation: To good ſouldidurs and men of warre that know theyr obedience to theyr Capitaine (and to ſuch as I haue ſpoken of afore)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> braue Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, gallant, curteous and ciuil, that haue their hand neuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Cap, and one knée on the grounde, ſo ſeruiceable, ſo obedient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with a thouſande courteſies, and as manys reuerences: ſuch are worthie the liberalitie of Princes: And not thoſe churliſh repyners, vnto whom when you haue giuen the one halfe of your goodes, they will thinke ſtyll you are beholden vnto them, and by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce refuſe youre courteſſe, to confirme the more theyr glowming grauitie: and as for receyuing any honour or reuerence of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15035:37"/>
them, it is as muche as nothing: yet will they not ſticke too malaperly to checke you, and ſay you liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uill, and will ſpeake to you as to theyr ſeruants. To be beneficiall or doe good to theſe ſurly ſort, is euill done, and is an extremitie of our vertue: whiche wée call prodigalitie, whereof wée maye ſaye with the good <hi>Ennius, <hi>Benefacta male locata, male facta arbitror.</hi> A good turne euill beſtowed, is euill imployed: or a pleaſure done to one vnworthie, is a hatefull vice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other <hi>maxime</hi> of our vertue is, too meaſure liberalitie according to oure facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or abilitye: For none ought too gyue ſo muche, as hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee compelled to begge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after: yet there are ſome of ſundrye opinions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſaye withoute reſpecte or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of goodes and worldlye wealth, wée ſhoulde not locke vp oure liberalitie, for they goe and come and increaſe dayly, and that it is better to be poore wyth honour and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, than riche wyth villanye and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I am not of theyr opinion. For the Auncientes woulde not, that in pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of anye, wée ſhoulde ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nable our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne ſtate, that wée ſhould take away the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane and benefit from ourſelues, to be able to be friendly ſtill: we muſt then gouerne
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15035:38"/>
our bounty in ſuch ſort, as he doth which ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the way to a ſtraunger, or he that ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an other mans candell at his: for the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher leſeth not his knowledge, nor the candel his clearneſſe: and I thinke the graueſt &amp; wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt ſort of our Philoſophers, wil ſoneſt agrée with me in this. And further, he that is faln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in decay, although by the ſame he haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued honor, &amp; is eſtéemed liberal: yet will it be hard for him in his pouertie, to continue that credite, and maintayne that reputation: for we ordinarily diſdayne the poore, and thoſe that be in neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>Our thirde <hi>Maxime</hi> is to ioyne liberalitie with iuſtice: for it is neither good, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nor decent, to be bountifull of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to others, and (as they ſay) of an other mans leather to cut large thongs: wherein wée muſt conſider of that wée haue ſpoken of Iuſtice, that to withholde, or violently too kéepe anye mans goodes from hym, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a gentle brauerie, ſo that the ſame bée cloaked and couered wyth ſome likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode of reaſon. For (as we haue oft ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> afore) the ſemblances and apparaunces of all things cunningly couched, are the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſupporters of oure Philoſophie: for ſuche as wée ſéeme, ſuche are wée iudged
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15035:38"/>
here: for by ſhiftes and ſome charge we may peruert iudgements and informations with cunning conueyance, but this is ſtraunge to ſuch as haue not felt the ſwéeteneſſe thereof, for we kepe this géere cloſe in our budgets.</p>
               <p>Alſo we ought to regarde, that in the vſe of liberalitie eyther wée doe the firſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or we acquit ſuch good turnes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as we haue before receyued: wherein when we render and reſtore, we muſt not in any wiſe ſhew our ſelues niggards, nere and ſparing: for thoſe obligations of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are no leſſe with vs, than if it were in a Ciuill cauſe. This is a great Argument to be obſerued that where wée are liberall, it ſhoulde bee done ſo voluntarily, and with ſo francke a minde, as the name it ſelfe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: hauing regarde too conſider the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of euerie Diuiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, to the ende the better too vſe our vertue: what wée are, how able wée are, and what they bée vppon whom wée beſtowe anye bountie or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: eyther oure Parent, Neighbour, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar or friend, or any other ſuch lyke. In all the Circumſtaunces there is one pretex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed poynt, that ſéemes of ſo greate efficacie, as it were a perfite and good loue grounded on vertue: whiche wée ſée to be finely flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15035:39"/>
in Gentlemen to Gentlemen, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to ſouldiers, when they are all Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, or of our Courtly crew, wherein it is not néedfull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nearely to regarde or ſearch the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; cauſes of ſuch friendſhip or friendly amitie. For it ſufficeth that vpon this fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of honeſtie, and Courtly ciuilitie, there be certaine ſhadowed graces and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of weake loue, and faint fauour: whiche may well be called (if the terme were tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) a fawing flatterie, that tyeth them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with mutuall curteſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the two other partes of Liberalitie.</head>
               <p>THe other two partes of our liberalitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiſt in diſtributing, and hoſte wing of Dueties, Honours, and Reuerances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whiche belongs to inferiour followers, and to the good felowſhip of Courtly companions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as for gyuing of aduic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and counſell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that belongs to the learned and lettered men, be they ſuperiours, equalles, or inferiours. Touching the firſt, they muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde that they be not ſparing, ſlanke or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, in lowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ointing and humblie reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuche as deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For then men
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15035:39"/>
might call them eyther arrogant, proude, or ignorant: neyther muſt they be prodigall to euery man with their ſalutations, in words or déedes: for ſo they may be accounted déepe diſſemblers, flatterers, or very ſimple ſoules. As for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lerned, they ſhould haue care, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enforce themſelues to giue counſell to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: yet not alwayes with the truth, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ording to the appet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and pleaſure of ſhoſe, they ſpeake and giue aduice vnto: for if they holde, follow, and affyrme their owne iudgementes and opinions, howe true and good ſo euer they bée, they ſhall be called ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate fooles &amp; wilfull headſtrong: &amp; ſo they can neuer come is the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our vertue This is very much vſed in conſulting with Lawyers of our right, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly frame their councell according to the humor of the partie who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they counſell. This is not onely vſed at theſe dayes, but in times paſt <hi>Cicero</hi> did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in his pleadings, as himſelfe doth witneſſe, in his oration for <hi>Plancus. <hi>In cauſis</hi>
                  </hi> (ſayth he) <hi>adhibemur, vt ea dicamus, non quae noſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a auctoritate coastituantur, ſed quae ex reipſa cauſa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> due an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur.</hi> They will haue vs in pleading, not to ſay at all times what ſéemes to vs good: but to ſpeake that only which ſerueth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, place, and perſons belonging to our purpoſe.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15035:40"/>
And furthermore: <hi>Non ſolùm meo conſilio vti conſueui, ſed multum etiam eius, quem defendo, &amp; conſilio &amp; voluntati obtempero. <hi>I haue not</hi>
                  </hi> (ſayth he) <hi>beene accuſtomed to doe all after my owne head or iudgement, but rather applied my ſelfe to the counſell, will, and opinion of my clyent.</hi> I ſée none pleaſe mée more in this reſpect, than holye mother Churche men: and not without cauſe, for moſte of them take great payne to attayne to oure vertue. And it ſhoulde ſéeme greate iniurie too learning, if the ignoraunt and vnlettered ſhoulde haue this vertue, too reſtrayne theyr affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to frame and accommodate themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the qualitie and condition of thoſe they talke too, better than the learned: much lyke the néedie Norman, that procured him ſelfe a Prebendſhippe, and yet ſo ignoraunt for learning, as hée could not reade: kept his Hymnes, Houres, and tymes of Seruice with the beſt: who when a friende of hys ſaw him chaunting in the Chauncel, &amp; knew his ignorance, aſked him how he prayed, and what he ſayd: I haue (quoth he) learned the Alphabet or .xxiiij. letters, whereof all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are made, and them I dayly and wholy deliuer, in my ſinging and ſaying to God, who I knowe may make what prayers he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15035:40"/>
will of them: But for the ignorant, we will ſpeake more when we write of modeſty. And that whiche wée haue ſayde of the liberall in their temporall goods, may ſerue well for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the Clergy, in their ſpiritual deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Therefore it is néedeles to recyte it any more. And nowe to the twoo extremities of this our vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Prodigalitie and Couetouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſtributing of goods &amp; magnificall expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, is towards vs ſo gracious, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and fauorable, that I know no way how to auoyde the feare of exceſſe in this vertue, whiche is prodigalitie. And on the other ſide, the auaricious nigarde and miſer is ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and reprochfull to all men: that to ſhunne and flye the euill opinion of the worlde, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this vice, wée muſte recoyle backe ſo farre, that wee become as it were ſomewhat prodigall. And if it bée tollerable too mingle golden gayne and profitee of mony, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie (whiche the beſte and wiſeſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers paſt would not do) wée ſhall prooue and finde the couetous and nigarde to looſe more of their goods by their miſery, than they kéepe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15035:41"/>
or get by their wretched policye. Therefore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſée a churle welthy or rich, we ought not to ſay that his auarice or néereneſſe hath gathered it: For if hée were like liberall to vſe it, as he is pining to preſerue it, he ſhould by the ſame (without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon) encreaſe his cofers with treble gayne. For as by his ouer muche care and diligence hee hath gotten it, ſo by his endleſſe follye and feare to looſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, hee leaues to imploy it to his greter profite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As when hée ſayeth,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fertilior ſeges est alieno ſemper in aruo:</l>
                  <l>Vicinúmque pecus grandius vber babet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The frute more fertile ſeemes, that growes within my neyghbours ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The vdder of my neighbours beaſte, with milke doth more abounde.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This is the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>touſe cauſe, hée will buy no more lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s nor beaſts, but miſerably horde and byde his money in the grounde, or locke it vp for allurement to Theeues. For euen as the ielouſe feare of fonde and fooliſhe huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, makes their wiues the more ſoughte vnto, ſhewing by their ſuſpicion ſigne of ſome occaſion, either y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe is willing, or y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe loues nothir huſband, or elſe ſome other cauſe whiche makes and mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s yong men to enter in aſſured hope of obtayning their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15035:41"/>
deſyre. So likewiſe, the pyning payne, and ſo nudging ſolitarineſſe, whiche wée ſée the myſer and couetous endure too kéepe and garde his goods and treaſure, wyth his head ſtill in his cubbarde, and his noſe euer in his coffer: ſtirres vp the hungrie théefe, and ſhowes him, where plentye is to bée pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by his pyking pollicie. Whereof it is commonly ſpoken: <hi>Malus est custos diuturnit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis metus, <hi>Hee that feareth, looſeth.</hi>
                  </hi> And Ouide writing to the ielious, whiche watche their wiues ſo narowly, dothe properly ſay:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quicquid ſeruatur, cupimus magis, ipſa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> furem</l>
                  <l>Praedafacit: quod ſinit alter: amant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The harder kept, the more is ſought, the price doth make eche thing a pray,</l>
                  <l>The thing that others way as nought, who ſeekes? we wyſhe not what we may.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>For the better example of this, I maye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge the cunning varlet <hi>Strophilus</hi> in <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> who ſéeing the greate payne and toyle that the moſt vnfortunate <hi>Erili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> had, in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his golde, carying it ſometime into one place, and ſometyme into another, fraughte with continuall feare leaſte hée ſhoude bee ſpyed, ſuppoſing there was good too bee doone, ſoughte the cauſe, and fynding the money, robbed hym of it. Lykewyſe,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15035:42"/>
the filth of this vice is ſuch, that there is non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which hateth not a nigarde, and are glad and deſirous too doe him all the diſpleaſure that may be: ſo that he lacketh the grace and good wil of others, wherby he might make a more profit. For (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayeth) <hi>Rerum omnium nec aptius quicquam est ad opes tuendas as tenendas, quàm diligi, nec alienius quàm timere.</hi> There is no meane more profitable to man to make him riche, and better to garde his goods, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the fauor and loue of euery one: nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing more contrary, than to haue fewe friends, and be in continuall feare. We reade amongeſt the Romanes of one named <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercus,</hi> a riche man and of greate credit, who for that he did nothing magnifically or ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, whilſt hee was <hi>Edile,</hi> (according too their cuſtome) fell into the ſlaunder and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche of auarice and couetouſneſſe: for the which he was ſo euill beloued of the people, that after, hée following the dignitie of the Conſulſhip, for this onely cauſe they refuſed him. And if we will conſider from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to our tyme, what eſtimation was ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer had of a couetous man? what ſayeth all the worlde of a miſer? the villaine will not giue a glaſſe of wine to any of credit or hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: or (as our prouerb is,) he will not parts
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15035:42"/>
from the dropping of his noſe: hée dare kéepe no companie for feare of ſpending: hée dooth no good to himſelfe, nor to any other: hée ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his otes in his owne ſacke: he neuer fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth but in his boſome: &amp; many other ſuche like hatefull reproches. In ſo muche, that there is no Gentleman, how noble-borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o euer hée bée, that is not reputed and accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a villaine, if he giue at any time neuer ſo little occaſion to be ſéene in any thing miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or pinching. So that I rather allowe, and better agrée with them, who haue theyr hartes ſo noble, their mindes ſo franke, and their ſprightes ſo glorious, that they will ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume their goods in braueries, pomps, and magnificall expences, than to bee ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſlye touched with nigardneſſe or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Couetouſneſſe commonly is hated in all perſons, but chéefely in Princes and greate Lords, to whome it is moſte conuenient and ſeeming of all others, to exerciſe bountie and liberalitie, where otherwiſe, the continuall taking &amp; receyuing of their right from their Subiectes, without giuing, diſperſing, and diſtributing agayne, in proceſſe of time they ſhall find themſelues to haue neither tribute to receyue, nor ſubiect to pay it. For who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better diſpoſe of goods (whiche that noble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15035:43"/>
Plato would haue had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that haue them? Howe ſhall men of vertue and valure, good companions, and ſmall mates, come by any parte or por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, if there be not bountifull giuers? following this opinion, ſome will ſay and mainteyne, that the riche &amp; couetous are théeues, in making that pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate &amp; their proper owne, which ſhoulde bée common to all men. It is not then without cauſe, that this vice is ſo much hated of vs, &amp; baniſhed from our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, wherein there is nothing ſo diſpleaſant, as not to be glad and willing to doe pleaſure. And therefore, howe much the infamy of it is greate, ſo much the rather ſhould we withdrawe our ſelues, and ſhunne the chaunce of ſuch extremities, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> leſſe of our goods, or rather (as I haue ſayd) to be reputed prodigall. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prodigall are more excuſable, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in our vertue, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couetous. And if we will well conſider of it, we ſhall finde none ſo prodigall (&amp; therfore the more reprouable) as the aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricious. For what may be greater prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, than to gather togither, and laye vp the goods of this commonaltie: and to take away from a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth the faculty to vſe it, &amp; by that meane to loſe it, and (as it is ſayde) caſt it into the Sea? for if the goods of a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15035:43"/>
bée not loſte from the profiting of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, at the leaſt for his lyfe, I cannot tell what may bee accompted more loſt. For hee pleaſureth his friendes, and benefiteth himſelfe as much with that he hath, as with that he hath not, and his riches are to him as to others, no riches at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wherby it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: <hi>Tam deest auaro quod habet, quàm quod non habet: <hi>The auaricious hath no leſſe neede of that he hath, than of that he hath not.</hi>
                  </hi> Then if his goods ſerue too no purpoſe, neyther too himſelfe, nor in the fellowſhippe of men: we muſte accompt it loſte, and béeing loſte, wée may cleerelie perceyue, that the auaricious and miſer, is the true and perfite prodigall. But to the end we will not ſéeme to allowe vnmeaſurable expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, we will giue bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, confines, and limits to liberalitie. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his offices ſayth, We ought not to gyue any thing, except it be either profitable or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie. So that profit and neceſſity be the two bounds of this vertue, which ouerpaſſed any way, we become preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly prodigall. But tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we ſhould thus ſtrictly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend all, we ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al make moſt part of our courtiers, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt praiſed, wilfull waſters, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding eſteme very wiſe. For not only thoſe which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume their welth, or make ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15035:44"/>
magnificencie without profite, cauſe, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, are not alone pronounced prodigall: But this vnquenche able heate, and vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire of glory, the whiche withoute all iudgemente and conſideration conſtraynes them to doe it, is honeſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d commeth of ſo good a nature, that there is attributed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, a vertue more greate than libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, which is called Magnificencie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of comes this tytle ſo excellent of magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. And moſte truelye when the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good wyll of any perſon dothe fynde and féele that whiche hee doothe good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, ſuche magnificencie is muche to bee prayſed, proceeding from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o greate a loue of oure vertue, and from ſuche affection too pleaſure others, that they haue no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure too thinke of nor conſyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes</hi> and circumſtances: the whiche feru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſlye the Auncientes woulde haue vs obſerue and kéepe in this liberalitie. And further, wée that doe long looke or muche muſe on things ſecrete and hydden, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the ſuperficiall parte and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde appearance of theyr déedes, ſéeing that by ſuche magnificencie they ſhewe them ſelues of minde the liberalleſte that maye bée: not conſidering the vtilitye,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15035:44"/>
profite, or neceſſitie, cunningly couched, and well couered ouer: howe can we but iudge of ſuch people all good and all honor? leaue we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſame <hi>Valerie</hi> the great talker of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, when he ſayth, that the two fountains from whence ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, is true iudgemente and honeſt good will: for the ardent affection and hote deſire to be prayſed of all men, can not diſcerne this, nor will not be ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, to conſider of circumſtances ſo farre off. Let vs compare in ſemblable caſes, the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue betwéen the father and his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and we ſhall ſée ſometime the feruencie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be ſo great, that without conſideration (meaning them well,) they doe marre and ſpoyle them, not hauing their iudgement cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by reaſon of this ouermuch affection, to diſcerne what is good or euill for them. Is ſuch loue and friendſhip to be blamed with vs? Is it not true affection? yes verely, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome others call it a cockering: So that if any will nearer regard the profit of the one or the other, if this amitie do not earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare therein, it can not be perfit. Euen ſo let vs iudge of the magnificall man, who if he ſhould conſider with himſelfe, how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable it were for him to do that he determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: would they not ſay, his deliberation
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15035:45"/>
ſmelt of miſer is? and how he had great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>are to loſe that he mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to lay out? It is not at this time only, or in theſe dayes, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> our vertue hath bin ſo meaſured. For do not the noble &amp; ancient Romains glorie to be atrbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificall? Was it neede full or profitable, to cut mountaines, and to make of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a a fyrme lande? Was it requiſit euerie mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that came &amp; ſayd, god mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ow my Lorde, to giue and diſtribute ſuch great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of money as they did? whereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>all doth well report. What ſhould I ſpeake par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of Pompe, of the Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aters, the Triumphant Gates and Temples that he builded? Is not the magnific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> knowne by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s gardens and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries? For this cauſe onely we haue them as a preſident of perpetuall memorie, and there is none of our Philoſophers that dothe not with great diligence endeuer hym ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to imitate and followe them, chiefly in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yr Antiquities. The honour of the Romaines was ſo great for theyr haught courages and magnificall myndes: as all <hi>Italie</hi> is yet proud of it. And if we maye after them ſpeake of oure ſelues, ſhall we not fynde among vs in our tyme, ſome whoſe ſumptuous expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes haue gayned them great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame? Let vs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15035:45"/>
conſider of the noble doctors and profeſſed maſters in our Philoſophie, whom we haue before our eyes for example, whom we muſt followe and allowe in all, whoſe authoritie ought to ſatiſfie vs for reaſon, as well as that ſame of <hi>Pithagoras</hi> did ſatiſfie h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Diſciples: he ſayde it euen ſo of theſe: they haue done it, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought not to be argued or doubted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be well or ſéemely done. We muſte vnderſtande<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that in their liberalities, they manye times conſider not what is moſte méete, profitable, or neceſſarie, but that their magnificencie maye be the more extolled. And notwithſtanding that ſuche ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe are not euer good; commendable, and according to vertue: yet haue they great reaſon ſo to doe. For (as <hi>Theophraſtes</hi> ſaythe in hys booke of Ryches) ſuche mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificalneſſe, is the profite and reuenewe, that we receyue of the goodes we haue, without the whiche (the neceſſitie to lyue excepted) I eſtéeme and allowe as well of pouertye as of ryches. Notwithſtanding, I knowe verye well, that <hi>Cicero,</hi> in hys ſeconde Booke of Offices, lyked not of it: nor Ariſtotle, who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryding vs, for that we wonder to heare howe that in the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſometymes in a beſyeged Towne or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15035:46"/>
Citie, we will giue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſterne for a ſmall veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of water, and conſider not that without neceſſitie (hauing both body and mynde at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie) we account not to conſume muche money for nothing. So eueryone hath his owne opinion, and they be not altogither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and approued of vs: for there is not ſo meane a Courtier that delightes not to make ſome idle expences, to the end to appear ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificall. And whereas in loue matters eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one principally endeuers him ſelf to ſeeme wyſe, ciuil, and beſt worthy, and ſuch we will here take him. Let vs imagine the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of two Louers of ſome continuance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, and conſider among<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all others, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this our vertue, how they gouerne and behaue them ſelues. We ſhall ſee the yong gallant, that (without any conſideration of profit or neceſſitie) can not finde robes richy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, nor ſufficient ſumpt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous apparell for to pranke himſelfe withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither rings newe made, or iewels new faſhioned for his miſtres: nor daintie meates exquiſit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate though to bancket hir. And ſhe for hir part, in euery paynt indeuers hir ſelfe to do the ſame. And though peraduenture neither the one nor the other can accompliſhe their whole deſire, for their poore purſe ruthfully
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15035:46"/>
pleniſhed: yet they will ſo do, that their talk ſhall not taſt or ſmell of any thing but all of magnificalneſſe, for in this vertue conſiſteth their honor or dignitie. I remember me of poore <hi>Clitipho in Terence</hi> who had a ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous louer and of a haughtie heart, and coulde not wring from his father, being olde, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and hard, ſufficient money to furniſhe hir, vſed priuatly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine, &amp; would oft de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate alone, howe he ſhould gouerne with cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, the countenannce of his loue, concluded thus in himſelfe, ſaying: <hi>Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il eſſemihi, religio eſt dicere. <hi>I make it (ſaith he) conſcience to tell hir that I haue nothing for hir.</hi>
                  </hi> Whereby we may ſee, hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was it ſéeme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous or néedie, and yet had no meane to ſhewe himſelf magnificall: ſo muche is this vertue commendable. The olde myſerable louer in the Comedie of <hi>Intronati,</hi> did not ſo, for he was bountifull in perfuming his gray bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, when he was at the coſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a peny worth of Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, to beſméere him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe withall: But God knowes howe his Varlet mocked and laughed at him. And as <hi>Ouid,</hi> writing to a couetous damfell, ſhewing hir howe he could no longer loue hir, for that ſhe was ſubiecte to gayne and luker, ſayth:</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:15035:47"/>
                  <l>Turpe thori reditu cenſus augere pate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Et facient lucro prostitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe ſuum.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVith beaſtly gayne begot in bed,</l>
                  <l>To enlarge the Dowre thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> gaue,</l>
                  <l>And ſet thy face with curled hed,</l>
                  <l>To ſhewe and ſale to euery ſlaue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Hereby you may perfectly perceyue, what vigour or force there is in liberalitie and magnificencie, to winne the grace and fauour of euery body: yet I knowe there are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinarie mynions, which make no little luker of their lecherie: but this muſt not be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be loue, that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thus lodged in their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious heartes. It is not euill ſeeming to a woman to receyue gyftes of hir louer, though it be ill ſeeming for hir to demaund: as their good Maſter <hi>Ouid</hi> declareth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nec dare, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d pretium poſcided ignor, &amp; odi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>It offendeth me not (ſayth he) to giue, but it gréeueth me when they aſke, and that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes me moſt. Was <hi>Lays</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> eyther wife or of good grace, to demaunde ſo manye Crounes of <hi>Demoſthenes.</hi> he allowes of it ſo well, that he woulde not after heare hir ſpeake, nor giue him ſelfe to great occaſion of repentance. Notwithſtanding the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15035:47"/>
is greate, (and eſpecially to perſons of noble myndes, and affected to our Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,) that the Lawes ciuil haue prouided for it: Conſidering that it is a great intereſt to the common weale, to haue many poore and needie Citizens: and that the ryches of the Prince, conſiſteth not ſo much in his coffers, as in the ryches of hys ſubiectes, they would that he who is ſeene or ſuppoſed to gouerne hym ſelfe riot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly, or to lyue ſo diſorderly as he myghte thereby after become needie, ſhoude haue an ouerſeer, and not accordingly or indiſtinctly of hym y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> magnifically makes vnprofitable expences: for if it were ſo, there would not be found in all Fraunce ouerſéers ſufficient. Thus wee ought to vnderſtande this ſentence, <hi>Intereſt Reipub ne quis re ſuama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vtatur. <hi>It behoues the common weale to ſee, that none applye his goodes euill.</hi>
                  </hi> For we muſte thinke that otherwiſe the Lawes or Princes woulde forbid theſe magnifycall expences, as euill of it ſelfe, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to vertue.</p>
               <p>Euen as one named <hi>Marcus Opius</hi> made a Law, that the Romane Ladies ſhould vſe no ſuperfluous apparel, nor wear at their eares any Kyng or Gemme of gold, weying more than an ounce, as recyteth <hi>Pomponius Letus,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:15035:48"/>
of the lawes of Rome: this lawe was ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for feare the Romanes had, leaſt by ſuch ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ornamentes their wiues ſhould be come laſciuious. It may be alſo conſidered, of that the Emperoure <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> did forbid to ſome ſort of perſons, that they ſhoulde not weare certaine coloured and wrought clothes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of late, the french king prohibited gentle wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Citizens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wiues from wearing certaine ornamentes and attire of golde (the whiche the Dames of <hi>Lions</hi> did much murmure and grudge at) and all is but for the cauſes before mencioned: for order &amp; pollicie in the diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and difference of apparell, according to the maieſtie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the perſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of great authoritie and force.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Magnanimitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are nowe mounted very highe, and attained near to the throne where our vertue is ſeated: and for that ſhe hath repoſed hir ſelf in a place hard to come to; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this good ſentence of <hi>ISocrates: <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis radix anara, fructus vero dulces:</hi> The roote of Vertue is bitter, but the fruites are ſweete and good:</hi> therefore is it, that the nearer we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch vnto hir, the more euill, vntoward and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15035:48"/>
ſharpe do we finde the way, vntil we obtaine the perfit place i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe: which when we haue w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nne, nothing will be hard and weariſome vnto vs. I ſay this, meaning to ſpeak of mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h is the ſame that makes vs ſo ſtrong &amp; aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, that nothing in the world (be it neuer ſo deficile or difficate,) can force or driue our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to declyne from the way of vertue. It is not then without cauſe called Magnanimitie, and thoſe that profeſſe it and embrace it magnificall: which is to ſay, of a noble, bountifull, and honorable hart: For what greater excellencie can the ſpirite poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idye, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an to be ſtill accompanied with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> like it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And for any accident, inconuenience, or miſfortune that ſhall happen, not to be troubled or vnquieted, but ſo to remayne and abyde euer firme and conſtant? One great argument of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous value of this vertue is, that amongſt all other things which are common as well to man as to woman, this is only made proper and incident to men, and contrari wiſe, ſickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and inconſtancie to women: Of the which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion many men are proud, and ſo content<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that for this cauſe alone they ſuppoſe the better of themſelues, and will be accounted wiſe: diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayning and contemning
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15035:49"/>
to heare the argumente of a woman, as though ſhe were a brutiſhe and vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creature: condemning their ſundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e follies, as ſubduers and vang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſhers of reaſon in themſelues, when ſuch defectes of nature be in both the one and the other. The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hortenſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a Romaine Orator, hath by hir ſingular vertues well moued, that women are capable of reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owe he it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that by meane of a naturall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> weakeneſſe, which is féebled in them for want of inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, they haue not the vſe of it ſo familiarly. Man chalenging magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie then as proper to him ſelfe ſhoulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſtéeme it a great iniuris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that be ſhould be ſo delicate, effeminate, variable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant? If we ſhoulde ſee a man marche through the ſtreate at noone dayes, in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites and attire of a woman, woulde not the world mocke him? And yet to knowe a man, without the ſame outward ſhew and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be a woman in déede, as was <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphrodites,</hi> there is nothing ſayde of hym. Wherfore do we reproue <hi>Hercules,</hi> when he ſhrouded himſelfe among handmaydes, but onely for that he left his manly courage, and yelded to womanly weakeneſſe: with the which attire, he could neuer frame himſelfe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15035:49"/>
to any thing or other purpoſe, but to beare the diſtaffe? It is not po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ible for thoſe, who haue then ſpirites weake and féeble in following this vertue, to attaine good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e any valiaunt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of value, what countenance or braucrie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o euer they make. This is ſhe anſwere that <hi>Helen</hi> made to Paris, when he perſuaded hir to go to <hi>Troy</hi> with him, and to feare nothing, vaunting him ſelfe to be the valia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nteſt and nobleſt warriour in the worlde. She ſéeing him ſo lapt and lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kt in loue, and enchaunted ſo farre from that he would ſéeme or profeſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he had no more the countenaunce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quod bene te iactes, &amp; fortia facta recenſes, a verbis facies diſsidet ista tuis,</l>
                  <l>Aptamagis V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neri quam ſunt tua corpora Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. bella gerant alij, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u Pari ſemper ama.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For that in brauerie you your maritall deeds recyte,</l>
                  <l>The truth is thus, that from your wordes your features differs quite,</l>
                  <l>For Venus fitter then, than Mars doth ſeeme to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loue Paris, and let men of force, go fight in fielde forthee.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15035:50"/>I would gladly eſteeme and regarde loue, if it were not the ground and cauſe of all this euill, and that it woulde not force and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the courage of man, to ſerue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vaſſall to feminine fragilitié: or would prayſe greatly women, if they loued more, and delighted more in the vertues of theyr friendes and louers, rather than in a forte of counterfet curioſities. But the doctrine of this great Courtiſane in his Art of loue can not lie: <hi>Parua leues capiunt animos: <hi>Houering myndes haue no hold, and light ſpirites are beſt pleaſed with trifling follies.</hi>
                  </hi> There is nothing more vndecent or vnſitting to a man, than to be no man. I knowe notwithſtanding, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Philoſophie, and that good grace whereof we will ſpeake heereafter, will not ſuffer vs that among women we ſhoulde be ſtill Platons: nor likewiſe haue vs in euery place to gouern our ſelues, as it were ſtill in the companie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> women. The conſiderations of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as of the time, the place, the perſons, and others (which is proper to prudence) will kéepe vs from this euill, wherein it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to haue this good grace. And the larglier to treate of this kynde, to the ende more clearely to ſhewe what ſhe is: we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate the ſame ſo oft ſpoken of afore, that the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15035:50"/>
end of all our Philoſophie and vertue (that is to liue according to the manner of the Court) is honour and good reputation: without the which, I ſée nothing that ſhould ſo much ſtir or prouoke vs to great trauell, and ſo torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs in this world, as that. For <hi>(as Cicero</hi> faith which was not ſtill <hi>Academious) Nullam aliam periculorum &amp; labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um mercedem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> virtus deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, quàm laudis &amp; gloriae: qua quadetractat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, quid est, quod in hoc breuiſsimo vitae curriculo tammiſerènos exerceamus? <hi>Vertue will haue no other recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for hir paines and dangers, than praiſe and honor, without the which why ſhould we ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great trauell, in this ſhort and fleeting time of our moſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etched and unhappie life? Leaue therefore ſuch as ſpeake otherwiſe of Vertue.</hi>
                  </hi> Séeing honor then is the butte and marke whervnto the Sages tended their deſire, and the only cauſe that makes man happy, ſhould we not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne all, neglect, deſpiſe, &amp; forſake all other things to come to this? Yes truely. Beholde here the definition of our Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to do good to parent or friende, further than the ſame is honorable vnto vs. And to feare no daunger be it neuer ſo greate, that ſhoulde hinder any actions, whereby it maye attaine to this perfection. By this I meane not, that no payne ſhould be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to get goods,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15035:51"/>
or that we ſhould not vſe our pleaſure, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence our parents, entertaine our friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> loue God, and hate the Diuell: But I ſaye and affirme, that if any of theſe be to hinder or leſſe our honour, we ſhoulde leaue them and not regarde them: for that man is not magnifycall that preferreth the ſlendes pleaſure of ſuche ſmall try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng thyngs, to the great value and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yches of honour. In this the Romaines excelled, whoſe haughtie heartes and loftie courages ſo muche imprinted this vertue in the myndes and ſpyrites of all the Countrie, that yet to this daye to theyr po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie it is a great pleaſure and glorye, as it maye eaſilye be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, that ſmelleth ſtill of libertie, a contemning of all thinges, a deſyre to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieue vertuous actes, and an vncredible patience. There is no iudgemente of the affections and inward diſpoſitions of anye, more certayne than by the outwarde coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and open ſhewe of oure lyuing. For as it is ſayde, <hi>Abeunt ſtudia in mores: <hi>Oure ſtudies and affections are tranſformed into manners.</hi>
                  </hi> Whereof commeth oure or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie graces, geſtures, and countenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whiche is eaſylye ſéene and knowne
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15035:51"/>
in all oure actes. And thoughe particularly e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rye one dothe enforce hym ſelfe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble and diſg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hys proper affections, as muche for the ignoraunce of thoſe he is conuerſaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyth, as ſometymes for hys owne imperfections whyche hee woulde haue ſecrete or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d (wherein principallye conſiſteth a good grace, as wée wyll ſhewe héereafter) notwythſtanding this diſſimn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is no practy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the affectious and opynions, common to anye one Nation, Prouince, or Countrey, or to anye one certayne ſtate of perſons what ſo euer. For ſuche affections cauſeth in vs one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I haue ſayde) by the whiche cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onlye euerye one in hys countenaunce will be knowne what hée is, and from whence hée is. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wée maye well diſcerue the Italyan, the Frenche man, and the Almayne, one from the other, and by theyr geſtures and countenaunces onely.</p>
               <p>And for as muche as ſuche opynions and manners of lyuing generally, are the more harde to be taken from vs, béeing ſo déepe rooted in, vs by continuance, as they are turned into nature: So muche the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15035:52"/>
more ought they to be eſtéemed, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igent of euery cauſe, for theyr honor or profite, can ſéeme to be of any other nation, eſtate or condition than they are. The which we dayly ſée do attaine great reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and atchieue their enterprizes worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as maye perfectly be perceiued, in thoſe that are ſpyes in the wars, an example meete and ſufficient for this purpoſe, though they in the execution be not regarded nor eſtéemed as they ought. On the contrarie, the moſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of people, albeit they haue the wiſdoms to knowe where and when to diſſemble, and that they are ſo magnificall and modeſt, as they thinke: to do well: yet are they maſked in ſo many follies and fond loue of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and are in ſo great a gealoſy of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that notwithſtanding any honor, repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or profite, might happen them by this diſſimulation, they wil ſtill be like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: eſtéeming it a great offence, to vſe any faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not in cuſtome among them, for feare to be iudged of any other nation than they are: And will be offended, if by them the ſtranger knowe not the vices and imperfectious of his countrie. But to returne to our purpoſe, the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ines haue ſo flouriſhed in this vertue, that they eſtéemed nothing for euill but diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15035:52"/>
and regarded nothing for good, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; reputation. And although there were many Philoſophers that ſpake otherwiſe of this vertue than we doe, ſaying that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; honeſtie conſiſteth elſe where, which we alow no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let them know that the moſt part are with vs, and of ours, affirming the onely bountie &amp; vertue hir ſelfe to bée in the good reputation of men: for the whiche the greateſt paynes, trauelles, and tormentes, were moſt delyghtfull pleaſures vnto them. And not withoute cauſe. For if wee haue care too keepe cleane, neate, and orderlye, oure outwarde bodie, regarding that it bee not bounde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: we ſhould be muche more vigilante, to ſée that oure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſpright receyue no villanie touched with diſhonor. Among all the remembred hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of noble and famous Ladies, I wyll ſpeake but of one, named <hi>Lucrece,</hi> who to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the little diſhonor ſhe had ſuffred by hir rauiſhment, killed hir ſelfe. What hart of a woman had ſhe? was it not vertuouſly done in regard of hir honor, to leaue life, &amp; deſpiſe death, nothing remebring the will of God? who woulde not (as ſhee knewe, and as the world was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of opinion) y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the ſoule ſhould paſſe out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>die, without leaue of him
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15035:53"/>
that placed it there: no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore than a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier may departe from vnder his enſighe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> oute of the Campe, withoute licence of his Captaine. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at, ie ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious fowles, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpicious pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es doe com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly gyue their wiues the picture of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce</hi> killing hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe. For the example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as they ſuppoſe) may ſtrongly and ſtraungely moue them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo their wiues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue greate delight to behold the ſame.</p>
               <p>Wée muſte not forget one notable poynt, in this vertue: For <hi>Cicero</hi> in his firſte bóoke of Offices ſayeth, that commonlie haught y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mindes and inuincible courages, fall into déepe deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of glory, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> affection of gouernmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, whereby they bée prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſtirred, and occaſioned to doe euill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo as incontinent they leaue and forſake this vertue. For (as wée haue fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore) if ſhée become ſtraunge, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rarie too Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhée is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o better than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, boldneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: yet for that wée meaſure not Iuſtice to ſtrictly as they haue done, ſo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the leſſe wee oughte, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo feare this conſequent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And further, if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de of man bée no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ftye and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ll very hardlye and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come magnificall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ld
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15035:53"/>
encourage vs too contemne ſo many thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and too bée ſtrong and conſtante in indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if it were not the deſire and hope of glorie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whiche is the onely ende of oure Philoſophie? Alſo who is too bee founde ſo ſenſeleſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> blockiſhe or voyde of reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that hauing atchieued any valiant acte, or worthilye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perfourmed any notable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe is not gladde and deſyrous of renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med prayſe? The Gods be ſo ielous of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they wyll and commaunde to be inceſſantly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> honored: As <hi>Ouid</hi> writeth to C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in his ſecond booke <hi>de Tristibus:</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fama Iouis ſuperest, tamen hunc ſua factareferri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſſe iuicat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aye laſting is the fame of loue, and yet he doth delyght<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>To gyue the trumpe new matter ſtill, his prayſes to recyte.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> likewiſe thinking of himſelfe, and applying vertue according too his affection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> chaunged his opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and acknowledged the debte: as wée haue noted at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this worke. The d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſire of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is ſo naturallye bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nouriſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithin oure myndes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that wée ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e well maintayne and appróoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophye is in ſome ſoote grounded on
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15035:54"/>
Nature, as well as the ſame of the auncy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntes. There is none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who haue occaſion to be prayſed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny excellencie, eyther by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, accident, education, or induſtrie, that is not wylling and deſirous to bée ſpoken of. It may bée aptlye ſéene in women, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they bée naturally baſhefull, ſhame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> faſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and modeſte, and that they dare not ſo boldlye ſhewe their affections as men: yet they cannot ſo diſſemble, but that they ſéeme gladde, and reioyce too bée called fayre, and for the ſame are not a lyttle glorious. As the Poet that knewe them ſo well, affirmes of them,</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Fastus inest pulchris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uitur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia forman.</head>
                  <l>Diſdayne doth ſtill depende vpon dame beauties trayne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And pride to hir alwayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as handmayde doth remayne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>And after in his Arte of Loue:</head>
                  <l>Delectant etiam cast as praeconia formae: Virginibus curae, grata<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> forma ſua est.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The prayſe of beautie vertuous maydes doe like and loue full well:</l>
                  <l>They like the name, they loue the form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein they doe excell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>This deſire of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> glory notwithſtanding ſhould not be inordinate, for ſo might it blynde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15035:54"/>
iudgemente in ſuche vayne ſorte, that the true vſe and knowledge of it woulde leaue vs: whereby it commonlye happeneth, that thoſe whiche are ſottes in déede, and not gloriouſe, ſuppoſing too doe worthilye and honeſtlye, (whereof myght proceede a kynde of prayſe and glorye) doe it ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, that they are as they deſerue, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the people. And ſurelye I doe not a lyttle lamente, too ſée this erroure ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in all men. Therefore wée deſcribe ſuche gallauntes by the glorious Souldiers, in the Poets Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dies, who were ſo meſhed in this kynde of follie, that they knewe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what they ſayde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor what they did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As he that vaunted the King coulde no way hée without him, howe he gouerned all, and that there was none but loued &amp; reuerenced him, ſaying thus to his ſeruant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Est istuc datum</l>
                  <l>Profecto mihi, grata ſint quae facio omnia.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Gods in byrth to me aſsignde this glorious gyft from heauen aboue,</l>
                  <l>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all things yeelde vnto my minde, my wordes and deedes all men approue.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And he yet more foole in Plautus, whome his malapar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e made tóo beléeue that all women accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him ſo fayre, as they ran
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15035:55"/>
in euery place after him. The patche ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be true, ſayd: <hi>Nimia est miſeria pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nimis.</hi> It is (ſayeth he) a greate paine to be an ouer fayre man. Héereby wée perceiue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to be glorious is not euill, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of it be not matched with folly. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Offices ſheweth, how the magnificall man ſhould not be mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>choly or angry, &amp; that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie doth principallie conſiſt in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deling of this affection, for bicauſe (as hée af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth in his T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulans) it troubleth &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other paſſion. And <hi>Plutarche</hi> in his treatiſe of Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thoſe whiche are delicatlye nouriſhed, are moſt ſubiect to fre &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, &amp; ſoneſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The fury of this paſſion was well ſeene by <hi>Hec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ba</hi> in <hi>Eurypides,</hi> and by <hi>Progne</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omela</hi> in Quids <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amorphoſis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this argument whatſoeuer it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to ſay, we are of contrary opinion: that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anye Gentleman or Courtyer bée wronged, cheefly when the outrage toucheth his honor or reputation, and hee ſeeme no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to take the matter in greate gréeſe, althoughe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can diſſemble, hée is not valiant nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>icall. And thoſe that moſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fume in any ſuche quarell, are men of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> courage, and thoughte ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yeſt of harte.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15035:55"/>
So that ſundry are proude to ſay, I am cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke of Nature, and accompt of this as a vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Temperance.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt fountaine from whence flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the perfeaction of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oneſtie, is that that gyueth force and light to others, without whiche nothing can bée well doone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And is called Tempera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, whiche is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of perturbations and troubles of the mynde, and a meaſurable mildneſſe or meane in all things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wherof I can particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpeake no more, but that it very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all the reſte, and is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſpring from whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our. The modeſt man is hée that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uery man, who tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th nothing in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or diſpleaſure, and frames his quietneſſe to all purpoſes. On the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, he that doth arrogantlye impreſſe in his ſprightes his firſt opinions and imaginations, &amp; will not any way yeeld to reaſonable chaunge, is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And of him it is ſayde: <hi>Malum conſilium quod mutori non potest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>The counſel of that man is euill, which may not bee alter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d:</hi>
                  </hi> For althoughe ſuche aduyce bée good and reaſonable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet it muſte bée moderated,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15035:56"/>
&amp; maſked, according to the pleaſure of others. Theſe kind of people we ſhold not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany our ſelues with, as wilful men, hedſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp; ſuche as are ſubiect to their owne affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: for ſince eche one, hath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his proper imperfections, if wée ſhould ſtill be obſtinate or ſtoute, and would not yéeld nor apply our ſelues one to another, nor ſupporte and footh one the other, there ſhoulde bée nothing but deuocion, contention, &amp; particularity among men. Therfore is it moſt proper to <hi>Prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> to know the perſons, place, &amp; time, with the reſt of their circumſtances. And this beeyng knowen, Temperance entreth our harts, &amp; mollifieth all the parts of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it not to ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ill, or be offended at any thing though the ſame be imperſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in ſuche ſorte, that part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye it diſſembleth, and partlie it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, and obeyeeth to all theſe cir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ances. So wée maye knowe, that thoſe offenders are vexed with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ees, with Ignorance, and that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſable when it is alone: and with naturall preſumption, engendred and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yndes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y this ſeconde Nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> treate: which opre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umption <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>det <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mildeneſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogant, and ſtubborne agaynſte others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
<pb facs="tcp:15035:56"/>
cauſeth oure anger to be obſtinate, furious, and ſpightfull in opinion. But this vertue expulſeth theſe vices, and maketh our hartes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eke, lowly, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, &amp; obedient. As touching thoſe that offende but of ignorance, they are (as I haue ſayde) excuſable, when the minde is tractable, the deſire good, and the heart milde, gentle, and not ſtubborne: for though good naturall people are ignoraunt of thoſe sircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances, &amp; know nothing, nor haue ſéen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any thing to purpoſe: yet we may then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue them to haue good entrance and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of knowledge, when they do not wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſtande in their ignorance. And for that we dayly frequen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> company, as are neyther found in our Philoſophie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor good Courtiers: to finde out ſuche we muſte note, that of all the foure vertues we haue ſpoken of, this is the ſame which makes vs perfitely to vnderſtande and knowe, when any are ciuill, honeſt, and Courtiers to bée lyked. Some are ſeene verie ſumptuous, and magnificall in moſte of their doings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers attempt great matters of a loftie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hart, to ſhew a deſire to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uenge their honora <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſte of nothingleſſe than of our Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is modeſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ractable and temperate, is not without the other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vertues
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15035:57"/>
alſo And to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ende that the force of this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue may be the better perceiued, we wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céed to ſpeake of a good grace which chiefly a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reſt ſpringeth out of this vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a good Grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>heſe foure vertues, that wée haue treated of afore, are the aſſured and certain cauſes, and very ſprings from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce procedeth honeſty, which we like wiſe call Courtly ciuilitie. Of the which ciuilitie well framed, &amp; according to the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances (that we haue mentioned of) applyed, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, borne, and nouriſhed this a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which <hi>Cice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> in his Offices calleth <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>coru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> genezale.</hi> And for that the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter to him ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſo confuſed, as it is not yet framed into direct and right rules: he ſayde, it might be better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed in imagination<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than ſet forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in wryting: we will after him declare that little we knowe, as well by wryting, as by experience. And to the end, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the difference<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> betwene Ciuilitie and good grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and vnderſtanded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All cauſes pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the vertues before mentioned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ciuill actions, though they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to all perſones: for the vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>everie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15035:57"/>
tion ſhoulde be digeſted, and moderated, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the circumſtances. This agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good grace commes of ciuilitie and honeſtie: whereby we knowe, that nothing ſhoulde preciſely be called good grace, vnleſſe it be honeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And honeſtie ſhoulde be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, according to our vertues before ſhewed. Notwithſtanding, oftentimes abuſing the terme, we attribute it to villanous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt actes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as when we ſay that a theft or pick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ric is done with a good grace, when the fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>els, and ſubtilties of théeues and theeuing is well obſerued. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayeth there are two kindes of good graces: one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to euery one of the vertue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as that which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, doth ſmell or taſte of any particular vertue: The other generall, proceeding from all the vertues, which is a certayne framing and agreeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the pleeſing of the worlde, where of we now ſpeake Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may pertey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and iudge that they are much ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed, &amp; are not of the number of our Philoſophers that will euer haue their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of great vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo they that will not make other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but as magnificall and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chéere and our countenaunce
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15035:58"/>
muſt taſt of Prudence, Juſtice, Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; aboue all of Temperance or Modeſtie. Of the which foure ſo aſſembled and vnited, is perfitely ſéene and proued to come a good grace. Where are nowe out l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtie youthes, that are ſo liuely and braue, and take ſo great payne to be gallant, that ſpeake friendlye, marche delicately, and looke loftily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing countenances in all, and ſuppoſing by this to haue a good grace: and yet are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of our vertues, whereof that good grace ſpringeth. Then theſe pleaſant appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, that proceede from the honeſt actes of good Courtiers, is this good grace? which cannot be deuided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vertue, nor our vertue from hir. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſo great force to come to this perfection of honour, as nothing more: ſo that you may ſee our Gentlemen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> honor and reputation among Citizens and Marchants, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent them better with their borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſuaſions, than any of theſe rude and ruſtickes can do with giftes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt morall Philoſopher, gaue one precepte among others, whereby wee might eaſily come to honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is, that we ſhould not maſke, or diſguiſe our ſelues, and that we ſhoulde be aſhamed to ſéeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15035:58"/>
in déed than we are. For (ſayth he) when any ſhewe themſelues other than they be, it is a playne argument they are of no value. And further their ſayning and ypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie cannot but be ſpyed. For glorie gotten in ſuch ſubtile ſorte will periſhe. And there is nothing ſo finely feyned, cunningly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, nor craftily couered, but time will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale the ſame: and all cauſes conueyed by diſſimulation, are ſubiect to tyme, and are of ſubſtance like white bloſſomes: wheras true vertue encreaſeth dayly, and groweth with time to immortall perfection.</p>
               <p>To the ende that this appeare not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to that we haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yde of Diſſimulation, which we affirm to be of ſo great force in our Philoſophie: we muſte better vnderſtande the ſentence of Socrates: for we followe him in this, and his opinion is verie good. True it is, that he that ſheweth himſelfe other than he is indéede, diſſembleth: and he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth, ſheweth himſelfe otherwiſe than he is. But we muſt conſider the ende of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, which will agree with vs eaſily. <hi>Socrates</hi> forbidd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuch maſking and general <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhoulde not appeere to be others tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we are and we alſo allowe the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re very fooliſh and raſhly
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15035:59"/>
ſpoken, to ſay that a Gentlemen Courtier hathe a minde to be ſéene or accounted too ſhew him ſelfe contrarie to that he ſéemeth: or to doe any thing to that ende. But <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> letteth vs not, that hauing no deſire to ſhew ourſelues contrarie to that we would be eſtéemed, notwithſtanding we diſſemble, and accommodate our ſelues to the imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euerie one, when the ſame doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vs daunger, and is preiudiciall vnto vs. For ſuch diſſembling is not euill, and in it is neyther deceyte nor fraude: but all good fayth, as it were done not of purpoſe to ſhewe our ſelues otherwiſe than we be: but to the ende to pleaſe the worlde. Himſelfe doeth ſerue vs for example, for although he was euer like vnto himſelf, conſtant and not variable, and deſirous not to be ſéene other than he ſéemed: yet was he the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler in the worlde. It is therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie great prayſe to moderate our affections, that they appeare not any way to others: and ſo to diſſemble and accommodate oure ſelues to euerie one: For this is an eaſie meane to wynne and drawe to vs the good willes of all men, whereof commeth honor and reputation. And although ſomtimes, in diſſimulation is founde an euill intent, as in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15035:59"/>
thoſe that vnder their fayre and fawning chéere doe couertly hyde hatred: yet for all that they doe not leaue to be good men and vertuous, ſo that theyr euill will appeare not too much: for it ſufficeth to vs, if the means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e good, vnder the which, he that deceyueth his companion moſt cunningly and ſubtlely, is moſt wyſe. We ſée the lyke in loue, which is a place where oure vertue and god grace is moſte allowed and beſt proued, as wée haue ſayde. And is not then this diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation requiſite and neceſſarie to gayne by the deceyuing of one another: as <hi>Ouid</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention in his thirde Booke <hi>de arte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Saepe virifallunt, tenere non ſaepè puell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Pauca<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi queras, crimina fraudis habent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile is moſt part graft in men,</l>
                  <l>in maydens rare to finde:</l>
                  <l>Moſt maydes are full of fayth,</l>
                  <l>moſt men haue fayth reſignde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>And further,</head>
                  <l>Non tamen expoſitas menſa deprendat Amator,</l>
                  <l>Pyxidas, ars fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em diſsimul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta iuuet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In place when thou thy myſtreſſe ſpyes,</l>
                  <l>hir beſt to pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy countenance frame,</l>
                  <l>The eaſieſt arte to beare hir eyes,</l>
                  <l>well to diſſemble is the ſame,</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:15035:60"/>Sometimes we muſt diſſemble, to blind the worlde, and to ſhadowe our hote affections with colde regarde and countenances, or otherwiſe: as <hi>Helen</hi> admoniſhed <hi>Paris,</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt his loue ſhould be ſuſpected, which he made to hir in the abſence of hir huſband Menelaus: when ſhe cunningly counſelled him ſaying:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>At tu diſsimula, niſi tu deſiſtere mauis:</l>
                  <l>Sed cur deſiſtas? diſsimulare licet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnleſſe thou minde to ceaſſe,</l>
                  <l>diſſemble thou therefore:</l>
                  <l>But why ſhouldeſt thou now ſtint thy ſute?</l>
                  <l>thou canſt diſſemble ſore.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And on the contrarie, to be open and ſimple, is méete for beaſtes and ydiotes: for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption being ſtill among vs, that is, euery one to deceyue other that moſt cunninglye can: Thoſe that with open hart declare and ſhewe themſelues not willing to vſe fraude, are reputed ignorant, and haue not the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to ſpeake to a man. For this the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes are beſt eſtéemed, as ſometymes heretofore we the French men were: yet nowe (God be thanked) they haue pretily learned to liue: And further, when the ſuttel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of diſſimulation, is ſubiect to reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We ſhould not therfore generally blame
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15035:60"/>
diſſimulation. For euill people doe makeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill theyr profite in all things: As O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſayeth <hi>de Tristibus,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>laring to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me women had euyll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d hys Arte of loue, the booke was not therefore the worſe: For (ſayth he) euill perſons abuſe the goodneſſe of fire, whiche is notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good. And ſo of all other good things.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>And more:</head>
                  <l>Quodcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> attig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſi q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt ſtudieſe ſmiſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d vitium mores inſtruit ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuos.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This facilitie of the Spirite is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be blamed which ſnakes man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the pleaſure of others, to chatinge and tranſforme hymſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For in ſo doing he ſhall be accounted wiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> winne honour, and be frée of repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſion euery where: which <hi>Proteus</hi> knewe verie well, to whom his diuerſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſis and oft tranſfiguration was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie commodious. Thus haue you principally the profite, whiche Temperance brings vs, for the better obteyning of this good grace.</p>
               <p>We haue declared howe particularly we ſhoulde gouerne oure ſelues in obeying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nowe wée muſte knowe howe wee ſhall generally vſe oure actes of good grace, without regarde of the complexions, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and priuate imperfections of anye:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15035:61"/>
A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amongeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aungers, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne companys<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or in a multitude or greate aſſemblye where dyuerſe are of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inions, which will not be content nor thinke it good that we ſhoulde frame oure following more to the one than to the other, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it bée not to ſome noble perſon aboue the reſt, wherein it is lawfull wythout offence to the companie, to ſerue and obey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I cannot here forget the ignorance and brutiſhneſſe of the people, who in feaſts, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quettes, and aſſembli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, gouerne and order themſelues, not according to the maner of the Court whiche is the beſt rule: but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theyr particular pleaſures and opinions. Wherefore it is not to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled at, if oute of ſuche a companye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye come diſcontented: when euerye one of the aſſiſtaunces hauing their proper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, contrarie the one t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it were impoſſyble, but in pleaſing of one, wée ſhoulde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and muſte offende the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So that if any frame themſelues to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theyr rule and common manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one wyll conſtrayne hys deſyre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> lyke well of it. And for that the Spirite is the principall parte of manne, hauing ys cert ayne mouyngs, whiche are the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15035:61"/>
euen as the bodie hath. It is then the ſame wée ſhoulde moſte care of. For if the mouinges be honeſt, and according<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> too vertue, whiche is too ſaye, if the affections are not contrarye too the foure kyndes, whereof wée haue ſpoken afore, but are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyted, concorded, and ruled by them, the geſture of the bodye wyll eaſilye followe, and nothing ſhall paſſe before the eyes of men, whiche ſhall not bée well done and of a good grace. For the bodye is the Organe and Inſtrument of the Spirite, by the whiche it doeth ſhewe it ſelfe, and makes knowne what it is. It was not wythoute cauſe, that certayne Philoſophers ſayde home that the Spirite is euer lyke it ſelfe, and neuer commes wyth more cunning, nor better learned from the Schooles than ſhee was béefore: For thoſe that are Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and Teachers, do not inſtruct the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Infants: But only open, and ſtretch out the cunduytes of the bodie, to the ende, that the Spirite being deliuered, may know and ſhewe hir ſelfe, whereby wée ſee that menne of weake and féeble Spirites, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not become learned: What payne and ſtudys ſoeuer they take, what tyme and charge ſo euer they ſpende, and what
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15035:62"/>
maiſter or learner, ſo euer they haue. The reaſon is, that the Veſſelles and powers of the bodye béeing once opened, nothing more can bée done: and no cunnyng indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie or labour, can any way alter or chaunge the condition of the Spirite. Wherein it ſéemeth too mée néedeleſſe, in a maſter and caſe ſo cleare, too vſe anye Argument, for too ſhewe whether the qualitye of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of manne, bée vertuous or no, when it is too bée knowne by the geſture and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde countenaunce of the bodye: as it were impoſſible for the bodye, to ſerue for a maſke or falſe Viſarde to the Spright, which is euen ſo. For where as ſundry ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Authours, haue deſyred to make vs vnderſtande the conditions and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of perſones paſte, eyther howe they were learned, wyſe, magnificall, or ſuche lyke, and woulde perfitely repreſent them and deſcrybe them vntoo vs: they coulde not otherwyſe make them better knowne than by theyr actes, geſtures, and maner of lyuing: As wée may ſée in <hi>Saluſt,</hi> who doeth ſo lyuely counterfeyte <hi>Cateline:</hi> and in the Poetes, who had greate delyghte in ſuche deſcriptions. And wée oure ſelues, when wée ſée a manne ſtyll buſie wythoute
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15035:62"/>
purpoſe or reaſon, wée ſaye hée is waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and inconſtant: and when we heare one ſpeake muche and lyke or allowe of hys talke, wée ſaye hée is wyſe, and of a good iudgement. And ſo wee commonly iudge others by theyr outwarde ſignes. For too ſpeake a truth, howe ſhoulde we otherwiſe haue the knowledge of things inuiſible, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and hidden: if not by the exteriour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunces that be preſented to ſome one of oure ſenſes? Then wée muſt néedes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the countenaunce of manne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth and bewrayeth the knowledge of his Spirite: the whiche can bée no other in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſhewe, than ſhée doeth forme them. Wherefore we ought not to blame the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liuyng of a learned man, wyſe, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull or liberall: thoughe hée haue not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, prudence, liberalitie, and other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the Spirite. And for that there are many whiche haue not the true knowledge of hir propertyes, (which is no other but ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or vyce) and conſequently vnderſtande not that it is parte of oure Philoſophie: this is the cauſe, that knowyng nothing of the manners, geſture, and liuing of men, wée commonlye iudge of them otherwiſe than they are. As of a yong ſotte or foole
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15035:63"/>
braynleſſe and full of prattling, they will eſtéeme, wiſe, pleaſaunt, and a good ſpeaker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and on the contrarie, of one prudent, modeſt, and a ciuill Courtier, they wyll regarde as proude, glorious, and of no vnderſtanding. Theſe kinde of noddies be of the number of the ignorant multitude, whiche are nothing certaine, but ſo blinded, that they followe in iudgement of all thinges their firſt opinion whatſoeuer it be. Of whom it is ſayd, <hi>Quot capita, tot ſenſus. <hi>As many heads ſo many wittes.</hi>
                  </hi> Agaynſt whom whoſoeuer will contende, is like <hi>Hercules</hi> fighting with the Serpent <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> hauing many heades, who as ſoone as he had cut of one, there preſently ſprang out in his place fiue or ſix more, as euill or worſe than the firſt. The minde of man hath two gouernours reaſon and appetite: Reaſon is the ſame whereby he willes nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie too vertue: and appetite is that which makes vs deſire all things, without regarde or cheyſe of good or euill, and ſeekes no other thing, but onelye for pleaſure. Therefore we ſhoulde in all our life, haue great regarde that wee take nothing in hande wythoute ſome honeſt intent. It is a <hi>maxime</hi> or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that the Sages in tymes paſt left for vs to followe: <hi>Nihilfrustra, <hi>Nothing in vaine.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:15035:63"/>
If in all our doings before the execution, wée holde thys conſideration, to thinke of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wée doe it, and to what ende: ſurelye there ſhall not bée ſo many repentaunces, as there is. And for this cauſe is it remembred that the wiſe man neuer ſayeth, I thought it not, or it repents me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not for that he ought or ſhould not repent him, when he hath done euil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but for that he atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peth nothing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration wherfore and to what end: after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, repentance co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes neuer or ſeldome. Therefore we muſt haue great ſore ſight that in all our a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; déeds, we execute nothing raſhly, and without aduice: which if we do, reaſon ſhal rule &amp; gouerne ſo well, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the ſpirit wil not deliuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir, any thing but vertue: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence this good grace ſhal then be ſéene to procéede. Euen ſo the appetite yelding to diſcretion, wil enterpriſe nothing in vs, but be obedient in executing the decrée and commiſſion of reaſon. Then theſe immoderate affections, whiche are ſo blinded &amp; inſolent, that they make vs ſubiect &amp; ſlaues to our owne proper opinions: ſhall be baniſhed from vs, as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uill contrarie to our Philoſophie: whiche is not but too pleaſe and be gracious to others, whereby is obteyned honour and reputation. A man
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15035:64"/>
thus ruled and gouerned ſhal haue his whole ſenſes frée, to ſtudie the beſt meane howe he ought to liue: and when we ſhall once vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and knowe our vertue to he ſuche as we haue ſhewed afore, he will addreſſe all his thoughtes towarde hir, and will doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which ſhall not be agréeable to euerie man, wherby be may receiue prayſe and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the worlde: which is the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of our deſired enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>Sée here the happie way wée muſt holde: and whervpon is grounded the perfite glorie of our Philoſophie. Sée howe the true and right Courtiers liue: which bende and bowe their owne proper affections to followe oure vertue, and he pleaſing to all men. Beholde the true fountayne from whence ſprings the good grace, which conſiſteth principally (as wée ſee) in modeſtie and temperance. Where are nowe theſe glorious vaunters, that try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in theyr imperfections and good heads? which will not (as they ſay) for any man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, doe otherwyſe than after theyr owne braynes? Wée muſt ſende them to <hi>Tymon Miſantrope</hi> that enimie of mankinde, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them cleane from our companie.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman Courtyer is none of thoſe, nor ſo addicted to his owne deſires, or ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15035:64"/>
ſubiect to himſelfe, but plyant like waxe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to receyue any honeſt or frendly impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For if it be néedefull to laughe, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth: If to be ſad, he lowreth: If to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, he frowneth: If to féede, he eateth: If to faſte, he pyneth. And to conclude, he is ready to doe whatſoeuer it be, according to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and complexions of his felowſhip and Courtly companie, althoughe his affections are cleane contrary. Yet in all theſe actions, he muſte vſe a prudence, that he do not any thing lyghtly, but ſo grauely and with ſuche a modeſt meane, as if he had double conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in it, regarding why, howe, where &amp; when, with all other circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. And that he haue euer in his mouth not to doe wrong to anye, but to garde and defende the righte of all men. And if it bée néedefull to bée ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificall, ſo to vſe it, as it ſéeme to be done not nigardlye, but bountifullye: that he haue his hart firme, faſte, and aſſured, not moued or baſhfull at any ſudden motion, how ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge or ſtatelie ſoeuer it be. That he ſo moderate and bridle his priuate affections, as nothing be ſéene to come from him, but curteſie, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, and humanitie. And doing this, ther wil preſently appeare in him ſo good a grace, that he ſhall eaſily draw vnto him the fauor
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15035:65"/>
and beneuolence of euerye man. And as all the worlde may perfectly perceyue, that by the exterior and outwarde actes, one cannot ſo well deceyue, or ſo eaſily beguyle the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt of iudgemente that is, if hée haue not theſe inſtructions in his mynde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute the whiche none can attayne too this perfection of knowledge. Therefore lette vs followe and rule oure ſelues by others, accuſtoming too doe as they doe, and make a good foundation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the firſte praiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in inuenting and executing in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſomewhat that is good: the ſeconde too prooue it good, and too followe the ſame that others haue done good by. And in ſo directing oure dooyngs, beſydes that manye will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte of vs as greate Philoſophers, and béeing knowen of the beſt in our vertue not to haue the whole vnderſtanding of it: yet at the leaſte they will commende &amp; prayſe our deſire to knowe the ground of it: whiche by little &amp; little wyll ſo poliſh and burniſhe our countenance, that in the ende wee may well come too the perfection of this good grace. Lette vs marke the Italian his Ciuilitie and courteſie. For auncient Rome the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and nourſe of manye of oure Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie (althoughe they haue wrytten of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15035:65"/>
haue ſowen and ſpredde in all the countrey certayne countenances and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, whiche are daylye practiſed in ſuche ſorte, as, though ſome haue not their mindes perfectly inſtructed, yet they haue their chere and geſtures ſo framed, by a cuſtome of fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it, that they ſéeme to vs the beſte for Courtly grace in the worlde. The Italian will not appeare in any his actes raſhe or heady, but ſo coldely and ſo ſoberly ſéemes to conſider all circumſtances, as thougeh hee taſted the ſappe and ſubſtance of oure beſte vertue; whiche procéedes of Prudence. And in dooing wrong to any, whereby the lawe may touche him, or the Iudge byte him (as wée haue ſayde ſpeaking of Iuſtice) he is ſo circumſpecte, as hée commonlye kéepes and conueyes himſelfe out of bondage euer. And if it bée néedefull too playe <hi>Sienor Magnifico,</hi> God knowes how he wyll do his endeuour. Touching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hawtineſſe of hart &amp; nobleneſſe of minde, there are none in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world do better or with more maieſtie repreſent it tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they. They bluſh or baſh at nothing: for if you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſodainly to moue them, with a ſhrinke of their ſhoulder they ſhake it of, &amp; make a good appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If you ſuppoſe to make them laughe, they will not chaunge countenance:
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15035:66"/>
And for the reſte, it is néedeleſſe to tell, howe they couer, hyde, and repreſſe their affections with their greate, pacience and diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So that to conclude, they are borne and bredde in their countrey Courtiers. By this example, ſuch as cannot well inſtruct their mindes in our Philoſophie, ſhall doe ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly well to endeuour and accuſtome them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to imitate, followe, and repreſent the beſt liked and moſte allowed in the ſame. I was of opinion too procéede in this matter more particularly, but I féele my pen blu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; wéery: &amp; I am willing to recreate my ſelfe in this countrey where I am newly come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will content myſelfe too haue opened thus much, by the which ſuch as haue good eyeſight, may as in a turrette or proſpectiue place, regarde a farre off, and ſée many things touching the varietie of mans lyfe, whereof we haue no whit ſpoken. Wée may alſo perceyue that this Philoſophy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that commaundes vs to do all things which is good faythfully and truely, howe it hath made vs to gather togither this, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15035:66"/>
we haue treated: which willes vs to doe the ſame, that ſéemes good to men. And this error is not to be wondered at, ſince it coms of the corruption and deprauation of oure mindes, who accompts that good which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill according to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of other men ſome what perfect. For wée haue ſo manye ſpyes and enimies, that ſéeke no other than to entrappe and meſhe vs in theſe follies &amp; vanities, to the ende we ſhould not know the true way we ought to take: that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for this ſecond nature (wherin the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and worldly wiſe haue ſette their onely good and felicitie) to reſiſt or withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them: wherby moſt part of men are deceyued, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to haue this Philoſophie, whiche they haue not. And others that are ſayde too bée more wiſe, are moſt abuſed: beléeuing that in the ſame whiche they haue, conſiſteth the onely good &amp; happy ſtate of man, whereas in déede there is nothing more contrarye to the ſoueraine bountie than their Science alone: whiche doth no other, but puffe and lyfte vp theſe our mindes againſt the alone and only omnipotent puyſſance. Wherfore I affirme that true Philoſophie is the deſpiſing &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of Philoſophie and his foundation, whiche is this ſecond nature, that God hath
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15035:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not made. For by the faulte of man it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo corrupted. If wée wyll bée Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, we muſte ſhake from vs and vnfolde the darkeneſſe and impedimentes of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde nature, &amp; hir conſequence: (what this conſequence is, I leaue to others iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) and indeuour our ſelues to reknowledge the firſt, which is the ſame that God made: who will gyue vs his bleſſing and grace ſo to doe, if wée open the gate vnto him who ſéeketh vs, ſaying, I ſtand at your dore and knocke therat, if any will receyue me, I wyll come in and eate with him, and he with me.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tente thy ſelfe for the preſente (gentle Reader) with that I haue opened vnto thee the gate of my thoughtes, and brought thée into the Cabinet of my contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: hoping (if thou take it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauntly) that I wyll ſhewe thee peece after peece, the remnant of the little Treaſure that I haue there.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15035:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> Henry Binneman, for Lucas <hi>Hariſon and George Biſhop.</hi> Anno Domini. 1575.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
